<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Death and the grave, or, A sermon preached at the funeral of that honorable and virtuous Ladie, the Ladie Alice Lucie, August 17, 1648 by Th. Dugard ...</title>
            <author>Dugard, Thomas, b. 1587 or 8.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36772</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12142740</idno>
  <idno type="VID">54874</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240953622</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6467</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12142740</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 761:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Death and the grave, or, A sermon preached at the funeral of that honorable and virtuous Ladie, the Ladie Alice Lucie, August 17, 1648 by Th. Dugard ...</title>
                  <author>Dugard, Thomas, b. 1587 or 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 54, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Du-gard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Lucy, Alice, --  Lady, d. 1648.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXIX, 48 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54874:1"/>
            <p>DEATH and the GRAVE: OR A SERMON PREACHED AT THE FUNERAL OF THAT <hi>Honorable</hi> and <hi>Virtuous</hi> LADIE, the Ladie <hi>ALICE LƲCIE,</hi> August 17. 1648.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Th. Du-gard,</hi> M.A. and Rector of <hi>Barford</hi> in the Countie of WARWICK.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Du-gard,</hi> Anno Domini 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:54874:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54874:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE</hi> Right Worshipful, and much honored, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <list>
                  <item>Spencer</item>
                  <item>Robert</item>
                  <item>Richard</item>
                  <item>Thomas</item>
                  <item>Fulk</item>
               </list> Lucie.
<list>
                  <item>The <hi>Ladie</hi> Constance Spencer.</item>
                  <item>M<seg rend="sup">rs</seg> Brigit Broughton.</item>
                  <item>M<seg rend="sup">rs</seg>
                     <list>
                        <item>Lucie</item>
                        <item>Alice</item>
                        <item>Elisabeth</item>
                     </list> Lucie</item>
               </list> The Remain's of that Honorable Pair, Sir THOMAS LUCIE Knight, and the Ladie ALICE his Wife.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worshipful, and much honored!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad this<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Filius doloris mei <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.48.</note>
               <hi>Ben-oni</hi> died in the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar, and been interred with the Honorable Ladie, it had made no addition to My Sorrow. Might I have had my Option, either the Funeral had found mee a silent Mourner, or these Funeral Notes had not needed a gentle Reader. But I was in a manner<note n="*" place="margin">—Scripta di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volgata sunt, Amicûm sum f<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> su, non me âpte audaciâ. <hi>Lips. Epist. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>st p.</hi> 20<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> necessitated, as before to the Pulpit, so now to the Pres<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my former relation to your Noble Familie, (where I had the honor to bee Preacher three years)
<pb facs="tcp:54874:3"/> not excusing mee from the one, nor your<note n="†" place="margin">Pietas non so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lùm erga De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, sed etiam parentes &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timè meritos usurpatur. Hinc pius <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas.</hi> Et illud <hi>Ciceronis,</hi> Ego omni officio ac potiùs pietate, &amp;c. sic <hi>ep.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 1. &amp; 6. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> Pietie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your dearest Parent from the other. Howbeit my slow motion toward the Press may bee sufficient evidence, that, although I have an hand in this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, I had no heart to it. Not that there is in mee the least unwillingness to serv you, and to do all the honor I can to the memorie of Her, to whom both my self and mine were so much obliged: But that I am sensible of the imperfections of my Funeral-service; (alas! what could bee performed by a man of so imperfect health, and withal so full of various necessarie emploiments, as I then was?) and am not ignorant that the endevours of my best health, and greatest vacancie, would have subsided much below her excellent Worth. Add hereunto the Distemper of the Times, casting great dis-respect, as upon<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Non solùm tempora iniqua literis sunt, sed etiam judicia hominum. Uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam fallar! sed ut haeres fluút, Domitiani e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto opus non erit; bonae ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes brevi in exsilium ibunt suâ sponte. <hi>Lip. Ep. Qu. p.</hi> 201.</p>
                  <p>Dixeris haec inter varicosos Centuriones,</p>
                  <p>Continuò crassum ridet <hi>Vulfenius</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geris,</p>
                  <p>Et centum Graecos curto centurse lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>Pers. S<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi> 5.</p>
               </note> secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Learning, the necessarie and neat Handmaid; so upon Sacred Divinitie, the never enough honored &amp; admired Mistress. Divinitie finde's but little huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie among manie men. Even they that heretofore have said, <hi>How beautiful are the Feet of them that preach the Gospel of Peace, and bring glad tidings of good things?</hi> and <hi>if it had been possible would have plucked out their own eies, and giv'n them to</hi> their pious and painful Ministers, are now readie to pluck out their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster's eies, and to pluck meat from their mouths, and to pluck them from their Pulpits, and to trample them under their feet. They cannot see so much beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in their Faces now, as they did in their Feet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore; when <hi>they saw their Faces</hi> (as the Council did <hi>Stephen</hi>'s) <hi>as if they had been the faces of
<pb facs="tcp:54874:3"/> Angels.</hi> They saie unto them, as <hi>Korah</hi> and his Complices said to <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Yee take too much upon you, seeing all the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are holie, everie one of them, and the Lord is among them: Wherefore then lift you up your selvs above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi> Numb. <hi>16.3.</hi> or at least as <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> said against <hi>Moses, Hath the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed spoken onely by Moses? hath hee not spoken also by us?</hi> Numb. <hi>12.2.</hi> and, conceiting them as useless and dangerous as the brazen Serpent at last was, they would as gladly (and think they might as righteously) break them in pieces as <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> did it, <hi>2 Kings 18.4.</hi> And how fare's it with orthodox, searching, settling Discourses, delivered to the Ear, and thence commended to Publick View? Never was there greater need of such, and never a greater neglect of them. Of Hundreds, each where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may challenge an <hi>Hic meret aera liber Sosiis</hi> &amp;c. it may now bee said, <hi>Quis leget haec? vel duo, vel nemo.</hi> Divinitie hath had of late but few Readers; and manie Learned, Godlie, Reverend Divines but few Hearers. Everie <hi>Ignis Fatuus</hi> hath been followed as if it were the Star that led to Christ: and everie blazing Comet more looked upon and delighted in then the fountain of Light. Rush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candles have been lighted at Mid-daie, and a crie made, <hi>O what blessed Lights are here!</hi> and the Sun, though shining in his strength, made nothing of in comparison. Now what<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Evils do these Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets portend? May his Prophesie prove the falsest that ever was, that shall fore-tell the extirpation of
<pb facs="tcp:54874:4"/> a learned and faithful Ministrie, the extinction of the liberal Sciences, the putting out of the two eies of the Land; our relaps into Barbarism and Atheism, and God's heaviest Judgments breaking us into pieces. O may wee never hear <hi>Lo-ruhamah, Lo-ammi;</hi> nor saie <hi>Icabod;</hi> nor see <hi>Magor missabib.</hi> Our provocations have been high; were our invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions strong, and our return to our offended God spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, <hi>peradventure</hi> our Land might yet bee called <hi>Beulah,</hi> and <hi>Hephzibah;</hi> wee might bee<note n="*" place="margin">Isai. 62.3, 4.</note>
               <hi>a crown of glorie in the hand of the Lord, and a royal diademe in the hand of our God.</hi> What will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com of us, whether wee shall bee a People anie longer or not, God onelie know's. If hee shall not forthwith proceed to Judgment, and cut us off, our iniquities beeing full, and crying for vengeance, wee must needs acknowledg that his Mercies are admirable, and that hee deal's not with us after the manner of men. If hee shall,<note place="margin">Felices ambo tempestivéque sepulti.</note> how gratiously hath hee deal't with your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>taking her awaie from the evil to com!</hi> Your Father hee took awaie before the late War, and so secured <hi>from it:</hi> Your Mother hee left behinde, and secured <hi>in it.</hi> Scarce was there anie Hous in the Kingdom that enjoied such a Sabbath from Sorrow as Her's did. For whereas most great Houses were deserted by the Inhabitants, not daring to continue in them, or to leav behinde them almost anie of their Goods: <hi>Manie</hi> rifled by rude Harpyes, and made as emptie as when they were newly erected; <hi>other's</hi> filled with bitter lamentation for abuses offered to the weaker sex, and carrying awaie the Master, or som of his Children: and <hi>som,</hi> either burn't down to the
<pb facs="tcp:54874:4"/> ground, so that their places know them no more, or made utterly unfit for habitation: It pleased God to free Her's, almost to a miracle, from all these mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Shee had <hi>Peace within her wals,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 122.7.</note> and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and prosperitie with it. Though men of War came frequently thither in great multitudes, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported themselvs there, and departed thence, like Sons of Peace. Their Quarters they alwaies left free, except from Free-quarter. Shee made the <hi>most High her habitation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 91.9.</note> and Hee blessed her Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place. Shee delighted in Him, and Hee in Her. Shee sincerely served Him, and Hee gratiously saved Her. Should new Storms arise, (and wee have no caus of confidence that God hath left of Storming <hi>England</hi>) you know whither, and by whose Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to repair for Shelter and Succour. <hi>The Glorie of Children, (Solomon</hi> tell's us) <hi>are their Parents.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 17.6.</note> Your's, having been so ennobled with all Virtues, that it might bee said of them, <hi>Deus est in utroque Parente,</hi> have exceedingly honored you. You will as much honor<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Them, and much more your selvs, by a livelie representation of all their Virtues. It is far more<note n="†" place="margin">Nè tibi ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scripseris vetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta stemmata, aut à majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus partam laudem: pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crius crit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, cujus autor ipse, quàm cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus haeres fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. <hi>Joach. Fort. Ring. de ratione Stud. p.</hi> 166.</note> honorable thus to reflect and return ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, then to receiv it. And this as it is alreadie don by som, so it is exspected from all. You are all looked upon as <hi>lucida sidera,</hi> shining Stars; whose motion must bee regular, and influence singular. The <hi>Irish</hi> use to require of their Children whatsoever Excellencies were in all their Ancestors. That you may do what is required of them, you need not go further then to your immediate Parents; in whom there was a collection of all the several Excellencies
<pb facs="tcp:54874:5"/> of your most antient and honorable Familie; and whom if you shall resemble, as <hi>Constantine</hi>'s Sons did him, to the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euseb.</note> life, you shall greatly honor, as Them and your selvs, so Almightie God also. Who require's to bee honored by all, but specially by them whom hee hath specially honored. Such as have the greatest outward Privileges, are apt to conceit themselvs <hi>privileged persons;</hi> and to live to Themselvs, doing nothing for God, that hath don so much for them. As the poorer sort of people in <hi>Swethland</hi> were wont to saie, <hi>It belonged not to them to sanctifie the Sabbath, but to the Rich:</hi> So som Rich, almost everie where seem to saie, <hi>It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long's not to them to serv, and do for God, but to the Poor,</hi> who have more<note n="*" place="margin">— meae Stultitiam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuntur opes, tibi parvula res est. <hi>Hor.</hi>
               </note> need of him. These must know, that the more liberally God sow's his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, the larger crop of Honor hee look's to reap. Do you, I beseech you, what you can for God; laie out your selvs to the utmost; improve your Talents, your Los<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, the Times. Your <hi>Talents</hi> must not bee napkin'd up; nor your Candle lighted and put under a bushel. Your losses are exceeding great. Parents are pretious<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theog.</note> Mercies; such as Your's, invaluable. When God made you <hi>Fatherless,</hi> hee intended you should the more look up to Heaven, and seek a Father there. Now hee hath made you <hi>Orphans,</hi> hee purpose's wholly to wean you from transitorie Comforts, and to make you more hunger after himself, depend on his Providence, cast anchor where you cannot miscarrie. <hi>Schola crucis schola lucis.</hi> Affliction is God's School, where hee teacheth his dearest Children the knowledg of his waies: the faster they learn, the soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:54874:5"/> they leav. If they profit not under one Rod, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther must bee exspected; if two prove ineffectual, a third will follow. You have been twice under the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rrecting hand of God; deprived, by the first stroke, of your Father; by the second, of your Mother. Som of you have most dear Yoke-fellows. If the departure of Parents drive you not neerer heaven, the loss of an Husband or Wife shortly may. The <hi>Times</hi> call upon us to call upon God, and to make our Peace with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, since there is so small probabilitie of Peace upon Earth. If this slender Discours shall afford anie fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to a right Improvement of your Talents, and Losses, and these threat'ning Times, I shall have the less caus to wish it un-published. You would needs have it; I here humbly present it; and shall ever bee</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your's to bee commanded<lb/> in Christ,<lb/>
                  <hi>Thomas Du-gard.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:54874:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54874:6"/>
            <head>DEATH and the GRAVE. OR, A Sermon preached at the Funeral of that Honorable and Virtuous <hi>LADIE,</hi> the Ladie <hi>Alice Lucie,</hi> August 17. 1648.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 89.48.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>What man is hee that liveth, and shall not see death? Shall hee deliver his soul from the hand of the grave? <hi>Selah.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Psalm is one of those Twelv that are marked in the fore-head with <hi>Maschil;</hi> that is, <hi>a Psalm giveing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It consisteth of as manie Verses as the year doth of Weeks, and hath, like the year, its Summer and Winter. The Summer-part is the former, wherein, the Church haveing reaped a most
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54874:7"/> rich crop, (the best Blessings of Heaven and Earth) the Psalmist breaketh forth into the praises of their gracious Benefactor, <hi>I will sing the mercies of the Lord for ever:</hi> so hee beginneth, and so hee goeth on a great way. Who now would expect anie thing but mercies, and sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Summer all the way' But Summer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, and Winter commenceth at v. 38. <hi>But thou hast cast off, and abhorred: thou hast been wroth with thine Anointed.</hi> Mercies and singing are now turned into troubles and mourning. But nothing shall you hear but bitter querimonies &amp; expostulations till you com to the last vers. There the good man com's to himself again. Though God were angrie with his People, hee cannot part with God in discontent. Though God had laden them with crosses, hee lift's up his head, and presents God with Blessings; <hi>Blessed bee the Lord for evermore, Amen and Amen.</hi> Hee blesseth him aswel for Winter as for Summer, for troubles as for mercies.</p>
            <p>And thus the last vers of the Psalm haveing as much affinitie with the first in matter, as the last day of the year hath with the first in season; if wee circle the Psalm, and bring both ends to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, wee finde a fit resemblance between the year and It.</p>
            <p>The Text is one of the Psalmist's Winter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drops; a black line from that Pen, which erst<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while was so filled with Joy, and wrote nothing but Rubricks. Hee complaineth in the next precedent vers, of the Brevitie of his own life:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54874:7"/> (it was like a Winter's day, verie short.) in this, of the Instabilitie of Man's Life: as though hee had said, I am not the onely Mortal. Other mens lives, though haply cloathed with more comforts then mine, and extended to a greater length then mine, are altogether as mortal as mine; for his Interrogations are equipollent to strong Negations: <hi>There is no man liveing, that shall not see death, no man liveing that shall deliver his soul from the hand of the grave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is death visible then? Hath the grave an hand? Is the soul subject to the grave? These I shall answer in the opening of the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>man liveth]</hi> What man of men, what stout-hearted, strong-handed man, what vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant champion<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> liveth now, or shall live here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And shall not see death?]</hi> To see death, as it is not a proper, so neither is it a common speech. It occurreth oftener in the New Testament then in the Old, yet but seldom there; Luke 2.26. <hi>It was revealed into him,</hi> (old Simeon) <hi>by the holie Ghost, that hee should not see death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee had seen the Lord's Christ.</hi> John 8.51. <hi>Verily, verily, I say unto you, If a man keep my say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hee shall never see death.</hi> Hebr. 11.5. <hi>By faith Enoch was translated, that hee should not see death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Scripture speaketh of Sleep, Eccles. 8.16. <hi>There is that neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eies.</hi> And profane Writers also, <hi>I have not seen</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Somnum hâc nocte oculis non vidi meis. <hi>Terent. Heaut. act.</hi> 3. <hi>sc.</hi> 1.</note>
               <hi>sleep with mine eies this night,</hi> saith hee in the Poet. And the Orator of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54874:8"/>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caninio Consule</hi> scito neminem prandisse, nihil tamen eo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sule mali factum est. Fuie enim mirilicâ vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, qui suo toto Consulatu som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num non vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Cic. fam. Epist. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Epist.</hi> 30.</note>
               <hi>Consul Caninius; Hee was a wonderful vigilant man, that dureing the time of his Consul-ship, never saw sleep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Like unto the phrase of <hi>Seeing death,</hi> is that of <hi>Tasteing</hi> it. Matth. 16.28. Mark 9.1. Luke 9.27. <hi>There bee som standing here which shall not taste of death, till they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom.</hi> So John 8.52. — <hi>Thou saiest, If a man keep my saying, hee shall never taste of death.</hi> And, Heb. 2.9.—<hi>that Jesus should taste death for everie one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chrysostom</hi> distinguisheth between <hi>Seeing</hi> and <hi>Tasteing</hi> death. <hi>Sed hallatinatur; eódem enim re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidunt,</hi> saith<note n="*" place="margin">Drus. Praeter. pag. 82. &amp; 133.</note>
               <hi>Drusius. Chrysostom</hi> is out here, for they are the same. And indeed so they seem to bee by that of John 8.51, 52. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior haveing said, <hi>If a man keep my saying, hee shall not</hi> see <hi>death:</hi> the Jews made answer, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham is dead, and the Prophets: and thou saiest, If a man keep my saying, hee shall never</hi> taste <hi>of death;</hi> where wee have an explication as of the one by the other, so of both by a third. For, as to <hi>see sleep</hi> is to sleep; so to <hi>see</hi> or <hi>taste death,</hi> is to die. There is no surviveing such a sight. Death saie's, as God once to <hi>Moses, There shall no man</hi> see <hi>mee, and live,</hi> Exod. 33.20.</p>
            <p>Now by this <hi>death,</hi> which all must see, wee must understand not <hi>spiritual death;</hi> which is a separation of original righteousness from the soul, with an Intrusion of habitual concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scence: nor <hi>eternal death;</hi> which is a separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole man from the glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54874:8"/> of God, and a punishing of him for ever in hell: (the one whereof answereth to the <hi>loss of Grace,</hi> the other to the <hi>filth of Sin.</hi>) but a <hi>corporal death;</hi> which is a separation of the soul from the bodie, or a dissolution of the frame of nature. Whether this <hi>corporal death</hi> shall bee <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>violent,</hi> whether in the <hi>morning,</hi> or <hi>meridian,</hi> or <hi>evening</hi> of our time; whether when wee are at <hi>home</hi> or <hi>abroad,</hi> and the like, hee onely knowe's that knowe's all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall hee deliver his Soul?]</hi> The Soul is a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, incorruptible, immortal substance, and therefore no meat for the grave's mouth. There are in these lamentable times, when Truth is cried down, and Errors are cried up, that make a grave for the soul also; and this Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others they make their ground. Such I remit to <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Tractate of <hi>Psychopannychia,</hi> and to another late one of a learned Autor, sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the <hi>Prerogative of Man,</hi> made by way of Answer to a Pamphlet asserting <hi>Whole Man's Mortalitie.</hi> Such doctrine cannot but bee verie comfortable to <hi>Flesh and blood,</hi> which <hi>cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.50. But ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie prejudicial, if it were true, to the <hi>Children of the kingdom,</hi> who, when they com to the end of their daies, expect to receiv <hi>the end of their hope, the salvation of their souls,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.9. And surely they shall not bee <hi>ashamed of their hope,</hi> Psal. 119.116. Assoon as they <hi>rest from their labor,</hi> they shall receiv their pennie. Assoon as their work
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54874:9"/> is don, they shall hear that soul-ravishing word, <hi>Well don, good and faithful servant, enter thou into the joy of thy Lord,</hi> Matth. 25.21, 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall hee deliver his Soul,</hi> in the text is, <hi>Shall hee deliver Himself?</hi> As the Bodie, so the Soul, is somtimes taken for the whole man. The Bodie, Rom. 12.1. <hi>I beseech you — that yee present your bodies a liveing sacrifice, &amp;c.</hi> So wee somtimes commend a person for a good bodie.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Sic Horat. Serm. lib. 1. Sat. 5. — Animae, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les neque candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diores</p>
                  <p>Terra tulit, neque queis me sit devinctior alter, de <hi>Plotio, Vario,</hi> &amp; <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio.</hi> Et Juven. Sat. 4. ver. 150.</p>
                  <p>— claras abstu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit urbi</p>
                  <p>Illustrésque unimas, impunè &amp; vindice nullo, scil. <hi>Domitian<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> The Soul, Rom. 13.1. <hi>Let everie Soul bee subject to the higher Powers.</hi> Matth. 16.26. <hi>What is a man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, if hee shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul?</hi> that is, <hi>Himself,</hi> as <hi>Luke</hi> hath it, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.25. So, Act. 2.43.—<hi>fear came upon everie soul.</hi> And, Act. 7.14. <hi>Then sent Joseph, and called his Father Jacob to him, and all his kindred, threescore and fifteen souls.</hi> So likewise, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 46.27. and so wee use to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a person for a good soul. This I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv to bee the Psalmist's meaning, and this might have been our Interpreters Version; who have els-where so rendered it, Isai. 5.14. <hi>Therefore hath Hell enlarged</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>herself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or, <hi>Shall hee deliver his soul,</hi> is, Shall hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his dead bodie? So the Original word is rendered, Hag. 2.13. <hi>If one that is unclean</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>by a dead bodie, touch anie of these, shall it bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean?</hi> So, Levit. 19.28. <hi>Yee shall not make anie cuttings in your flesh for</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>the dead.</hi> And, <hi>Levit.</hi> 21.1. <hi>Num.</hi> 5.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.6, 7. And so it might have been rendered here.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54874:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>From the hand.]</hi> By Hand, as in<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mensa Regis Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia. <hi>apud He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, — magnâ vi, &amp;c. <hi>apud Homerum Iliad. o.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Quàm velis eum obligare, in tuâ manu est. <hi>Cicero Epist.</hi> 6. <hi>lib.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p>In manibus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stris quantus sit Caesar habetis. <hi>Lucan. lib.</hi> 1.</p>
               </note> Secular, so in Sacred Writeings, is most frequently signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Power. <hi>Behold, thy maid is in thy hand,</hi> saie's <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Sarah,</hi> Gen. 16.6. <hi>My times are in thy hand; deliver mee from the hand of mine enemie,</hi> saie's <hi>David</hi> to God, Psal. 31.15. <hi>Upon himself put not forth thine hand,</hi> saie's God to Satan con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Job,</hi> Job 1.12.</p>
            <p>The Original word for <hi>Hand</hi> is somtimes rendered <hi>Power, Behold, all that hee hath is in thy</hi> Power, <hi>Job</hi> 1.12. <hi>God will redeem my soul from the</hi> power <hi>of the grave,</hi> Psal. 49.15. <hi>I will ransom them from the</hi> power <hi>of the grave,</hi> Hos. 13.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Hand</hi> wee meet with somtimes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: <hi>It is in the</hi> power <hi>of mine</hi> hand <hi>to do you hurt,</hi> saie's <hi>Laban</hi> to <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 31.29. <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold not good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the</hi> power <hi>of thine</hi> hand <hi>to do it,</hi> Prov. 3.27. so also <hi>Micah</hi> 2.1.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Hand</hi> of the <hi>grave</hi> here is meant the <hi>Power</hi> of it: and therefore it is so rendered, <hi>Psal.</hi> 49.15. and <hi>Hos.</hi> 13.14. But whether an <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending</hi> or an <hi>holding Power?</hi> If the former, then the second question import's no more then the first, but rather the later. And so, <hi>Death,</hi> like a Serjeant, apprehend's and arrest's men; the <hi>Grave,</hi> as a Jaylor, receive's them. Death hath hands and feet, to go about and bring men in; the grave an hand to hold them when they are so brought. There is no breaking prison, no escapeing out of this hand, until the <hi>Judg of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54874:10"/> all the earth</hi> shall give command for a general <hi>gaol-deliverie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the grave.]</hi> The original word signifie's <hi>Hell</hi> also; and it is most frequently so rendered. The Root signifie's <hi>to ask, require, &amp;c. Hell</hi> and the <hi>Grave</hi> are ever <hi>asking,</hi> and never satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.30. and 30.15, 16. They laie claim to all men, as beeing now fitter for them then for a better place. The <hi>Grave</hi> saie's, Give mee those wretched mortals, so unworthie to breathe in the Air, and to bee above ground, that I may cover them from the face of the Sun. Nay, saie's <hi>Hell,</hi> That is not bad enough; give them mee that I may torment them to all eternitie. <hi>Hell</hi> laie's claim to all, but receiv's onely som: onely the wicked; of whom it may bee said, as it was of <hi>Judas,</hi> that they go <hi>to their own place, Act.</hi> 1.25. The <hi>Grave</hi> laie's claim to all, and receiv's all; the wicked and the godlie too: one as well as another, as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid faie's, the sword devour's, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.25. For, <hi>what man is hee that liveth, and shall not see death? Shall hee deliver his soul from the hand of the Grave? Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Selah.]</hi> Is set to as a seal. It is used onely in the <hi>Psalms,</hi> and the Prophecie of <hi>Habakkuk. Soin</hi> conceiv it is never used but where the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is verie remarkable, and calleth for more then ordinarie observation and consideration. <hi>Som,</hi> that it is the same with <hi>Amen,</hi> and note's a belief of, and a willing submission to what is spoken. <hi>Som</hi> that it is onely a Musical note,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54874:10"/> signifying a letting down or lifting up of the voice, together with an elevation of the heart to God.</p>
            <p>You have the words opened. Wee have in them two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Maschil,</hi> or a <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Selah,</hi> or an <hi>Use.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Doctrine in the two Questions, where wee have.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Man liveing.</item>
               <item>2. A necessitie of his death.</item>
               <item>3. His Grave.</item>
               <item>4. His impotencie to recover Life and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All which may well bee contracted into these two.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Death's unavoidableness,</hi> in the former Question.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Life's irrecoverableness,</hi> in the later.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And these two (especially, if there bee such a coïncidence and identitie in the two Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as was in <hi>Pharao's</hi> two dreams,) may bee clap't together, or shrunk into this one, namely, <hi>Man's mortalitie.</hi> And so they commend unto us this Point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No man liveing shall live alwaies.</hi> Or,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Everie man liveing is a mortal man.</hi> Or, (if you will have it in the words of the Text)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Everie man liveing must see death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Use, in the word <hi>Selah,</hi> stirreth us up to four duties.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Seriously to consider our mortal condition.</item>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54874:11"/>
               <item>2. Stedfastly to beleev it.</item>
               <item>3. Patiently to submit to it.</item>
               <item>4. Wisely to improov it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>These I purpose not to handle severally, but to weav them into my discours of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named principal Point, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Everie man liveing is a mortal man;</hi> or, <hi>must see death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But, as som heretofore have not seen Death, so manie hereafter shall not see it. <hi>Enoch,</hi> (whose years were of the same number with the daies of the year) was <hi>translated, and did not see it,</hi> Gen. 5.24. Heb. 11.5. <hi>Elijah</hi> was <hi>put into a chariot of fire, and went up by a whirl-winde into heaven,</hi> 2 King. 2.11. and did not see it. And the Apostle telleth us, 1 Cor. 15.51. <hi>Wee shall not all sleep.</hi> So also, 1 Thes. 15, &amp; 17. <hi>Wee which are alive and remain unto the comming of the Lord, shall not prevent them which are asleep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Solut.</note>I answer. First concerning <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elijah,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That som conceiv, that these did <hi>see death;</hi> that the one was dissolved without anie pain when God took his soul. And that the other had his bodie burnt in his fierie chariot.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That, if they did not <hi>see</hi> death, (as it is more probable that they did not) yet they were <hi>Mortal,</hi> and as <hi>subject to death</hi> as anie that ever actually died.</p>
            <p>Secondly, concerning them that shall bee found alive at the comming of Christ.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That though they shall not <hi>sleep,</hi> they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54874:11"/> shall bee <hi>changed:</hi> so the Apostle telleth us, in that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51. And that change shall bee in stead of Death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is sufficient that they are by nature <hi>obnoxious</hi> unto Death; haveing by sin deserved it, and Hell after it. And although by their sudden change they shall bee free'd from <hi>Death,</hi> yet from <hi>Hell</hi> they shall not; unless there bee wrought in them before that change, a <hi>spiritual</hi> change; and so a <hi>meetness</hi> for Heaven.</p>
            <p>The Reason of the Point is rendred by the Apostle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>By one man sin entered into the world, and death by sin.</hi> So <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>The wages of sin is death.</hi> This is the woful wages which God threatned to the first wicked work, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Of the tree of knowledg of good and evil thou shalt not eat; for in the daie that thou eatest thereof, thou shalt die the death.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, so <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odotian</hi> render's it. <hi>Mortalis eris,</hi> so <hi>Symmachus,</hi> i. e. <hi>Thou shalt bee mortal.</hi> Others that do not so render it, yet so expound it: as <hi>Vatablus, Junius, Mercerus,</hi> and manie more.</p>
            <p>Should wee not then have been <hi>mortal,</hi> or <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>1</label> obnoxious to death if <hi>Adam</hi> had not sinned?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pelagians</hi> indeed affirm that wee should. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> They say <hi>Adam</hi> was created mortal. But the <hi>Milevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Quicunque di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Adam pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum hominem mortalem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, ità ut sive peccaret sive non peccaret, more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur in corpore, hoc est, de corpore exiret, non peccati merito, fed necessitate naturae, Anathema sit. <hi>Carranz. Summa Milevet. Concil. c.</hi> 1.</note>
               <hi>Council</hi> hath set an <hi>Anathema</hi> on their heads for it. <hi>Whosoever shall affirm</hi> (saith the Council) <hi>that</hi> Adam <hi>was created mortal, so that whether hee had sinned or not, there was a necessitie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54874:12"/> of dying, let him hee accursed. For man was created to life; hee was created after the image of God; a part whereof is immortalitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, if man, continuing in the state of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, had died; it had com to pass either<note n="*" place="margin">Vide sis. Arch. Rubeum in lib. <hi>2.</hi> Sentent. dist. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> through the disagreement of <hi>Elements,</hi> out of which his bodie is compounded; or through the consumption of <hi>radical moisture;</hi> or through som external <hi>lesion</hi> or hurt. But it could not have com to pass anie of these waies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, not through the disagrement of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> For 1. against such a disagreement, hee had an excellent temper, and perfect health: so that one qualitie had not anie destructive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominancie over another. 2. Hee had such an excellent power bestowed on his soul, that it could preserv his bodie from all distemper of humors, and all manner of infirmities what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, nor through the decaie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption of radical moisture</hi> For the radical moisture which was <hi>impaired</hi> by the natural heat, was <hi>repaired</hi> by his dailie food. And that Repairs might bee made equivalent to Losses, God provided the <hi>Tree of Life.</hi> Hence is that of <hi>Augustin,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Cibus aderat homininè esuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret; potus, nè si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti et; Lignum Vitae, nè illum senectus dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veret. <hi>Aug. de Civ Dei. l.</hi> 24.</note>
               <hi>Adam had meat, that hee might not hunger; drink, that hee might not thirst; the Tree of Life, that hee might bee preserved from old age, and from death.</hi> This Tree of Life did so comfort and confirm his conversive and nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive facultie, that it could not possibly bee weakened and fail: and consequently the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54874:12"/> approach of old age and death must needs have been hindered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, nor through anie external lesion or hurt.</hi> For 1. against extrinsecal Elements, hee had a most convenient temper of Air. 2. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the injurie of evil Angels, hee had a guard of good ones. 3. All the beasts were then milde, and gentle, and obedient to him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his dominion over them. 4. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all other things casually hurtful, hee had a great measure of prudence; so that hee could beware of them. 5. When mankinde had been increased and multiplied, all should have been just, and free from sin; none should have had the least injurious thought against his brother: if anie had offended that waie, hee had been presently expelled Paradise, as our first Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were.</p>
            <p>In one word wee may saie, That if man had <hi>continued</hi> in the state of Innocencie, his <hi>bodie</hi> had been preserved from all <hi>internal</hi> passion by his soul: and from all <hi>external,</hi> by the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God. Therefore it is evident, that if hee had not faln, hee had not actually died. <hi>Death is the daughter of disobedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since man, if hee had continued in the state <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>2</label> of Innocencie, had not died, but had been immortal: What would have becom of him? Whether should hee have continued in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise still or not?</p>
            <p>No, hee should not. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> The Tree of Life was unto <hi>Adam</hi> a symbolical<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Ainsworth in Gen. <hi>2.9.</hi>
               </note> Tree; a <hi>sign,</hi> as of a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54874:13"/> blessed <hi>natural life</hi> in Paradise for a time, so of a <hi>spiritual life</hi> afterward in Heaven for ever, if hee continued in his obedience to God. <hi>After a</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Corpore simul &amp; animâ, post-quam diu sine labore ac mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiâ vixisset, in coelum translatus fuisset, ad aeterna cum Deo gaudia percipienda, &amp; Dei essentiâ fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum <hi>Merc. in Gen,</hi> 2.17.</note>
               <hi>long life led without labor and molestation, both bodie and soul had been translated into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> saith <hi>Mercer.</hi> And <hi>Polanus,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Corpus Adami pulcerrimâ mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione, sine mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, in aeterna<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> incorruptibilica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem à Deo trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatum fuis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pelan. Syntog. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 28.</note>
               <hi>God hat<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi> Adam's <hi>bodie by a most excellent change without death, into eternal incorruptibilitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The sum of all that hath been said, is this.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>that man, everie man is mortal:</hi> and that an exemption from Death, is no exemption from subjectedness or obnoxiousness unto Death.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That man, had hee not sinned, had not been mortal. Mortal</hi> indeed hee was before his fall, <hi>potentiâ moriendi,</hi> by a possibilitie of dying. <hi>Erat posse mori, quia erat posse peccare.</hi> Death was possible, becaus sin was possible. <hi>Mortal</hi> hee was not <hi>necessitate naturae,</hi> by anie necessitie of nature: for his Bodie was of an excellent temper and constitution; his Humors were of so sweet an <hi>harmonie,</hi> that there was not the least <hi>jarring</hi> and disagreement among them. Yea, his <hi>Soul</hi> had power to preserv his Bodie from <hi>Death,</hi> so long as it preserved it self from <hi>sin.</hi> His radical moisture had been <hi>repaired</hi> by his food, as fast as <hi>impaired</hi> by his natural heat: the fruit of the Tree of Life had been as great a <hi>comfort</hi> to his nutritive facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as the <hi>honie</hi> was to fainting <hi>Jonathan.</hi> Neither Devils, nor beasts, nor anie thing had don him anie harm. Devils could not, beeing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54874:13"/> hindered by tutelarie Angels. Beasts would not, beeing readie to yeeld unto him all obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Against <hi>casual</hi> inconveniences, God's <hi>providence,</hi> and his own <hi>prudence</hi> had been his <hi>protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>that man, if hee had not sinned, but continued immortal, should not have continued al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in Paradise;</hi> but at last should have been <hi>remooved</hi> into the place and presence of God.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>Selah,</hi> or Application.</p>
            <p>Use 1. <hi>Since man is mortal, and must see death, Let us make no more of man then hee is.</hi> Apt wee are, (and it is our follie that wee are so apt) to <hi>magnifie</hi> overmuch, yea, to <hi>deïfie</hi> man. <hi>The voice of a god, and not of a man!</hi> was the blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous voice of the foolish people concerning <hi>Herod, Acts</hi> 12.22. But the Angel of the Lord <hi>confuted</hi> their conceit, by<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>confounding</hi> that so much magnified and admired Majestie. The people proclaimed him <hi>immortal;</hi> the Angel and the worms echoëd, <hi>mortal.</hi> The Angel smote him, the worms ate him, and that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately. Never was there a more certain and sudden demonstration of mortalitie then that was: and it may forever deterr men from makeing more of themselvs or others, then they ought to do. Three waies wee make more of men then wee ought: by excessive <hi>Fear,</hi> excessive <hi>Delight,</hi> excessive <hi>Confidence.</hi> All which wee must beware of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, of excessive Fear.</hi> And since man is a mortal thing, why should hee bee so terrible
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54874:14"/> unto us? See how God speak's to him that fear's man too much, <hi>Isa.</hi> 51.12, 13. <hi>Who art thou that thou shouldest bee afraid of a man that shall die, and of the son of man that shall bee made as grass? And hast feared continually everie daie, becaus of the furie of the oppressor, as if hee were readie to destroie? And where is the furie of the oppressor?</hi> As if God had said, What a fool art thou to bee afraid of a mortal man? to make as if hee were immortal and almightie. <hi>Furious oppressors</hi> there <hi>are,</hi> but suddenly they <hi>are not:</hi> for, <hi>where is the furie of the oppressor?</hi> both his furie and himself shall com to nothing: hee shall bee cut down as the grass, and his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie must then fall with him. Such a fear of man our Savior forbid's us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28. <hi>Fear not them which kill the bodie, but are not able to kill the soul.</hi> There are that make themselvs Gods, in killing the bodie; but they are not so much to bee feared, becaus they are not able to reach the soul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Wee must beware of excessive Delight.</hi> And since man is a mortal thing, why should hee bee so much delighted in as commonly hee is? God allow's us to delight in one another; friend in friend, husband in wife, wife in hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, parents in children, children in parents, &amp;c. But our delight must bee <hi>moderate;</hi> wee must not forget that such objects are mortal. And wee shall do well to consider, that<note n="*" place="margin">Immodicis bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis est aetas, &amp; rara senectus. <hi>Mart. Epig.</hi> 29. <hi>lib.</hi> 6.</note>
               <hi>immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate</hi> delight in them is the next waie to lose them, and ourselvs too. How often hath God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54874:14"/> taken away <hi>a dear</hi> yoke-fellow, a childe, a friend, becaus hee hath been <hi>too dear,</hi> and too much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in! Yea, how often hath the heart broke, when it hath been too much dilated and let out! 'Tis true, that of<note n="*" place="margin">Quem res plus nimio delectave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re secundae, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatae quatient; si quid mirabere, pones invitus. <hi>Hor. Ep.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 1.</note>
               <hi>Flaccus, Answerable to our affection while wee enjoie a comfort, will bee our affliction when wee are deprived of it.</hi> And as good counsel, that of<note n="†" place="margin">Quicquid amas cupias non pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuisse nimis. <hi>Mart. Ep.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 6.</note>
               <hi>Martial, Whatsoever thou delightest in, delight not in it too much.</hi> It is wisdom (and so our dutie) to suffer our hearts so to <hi>laie hold</hi> on a comfort, that they may <hi>let it go</hi> again without anie eminent prejudice; so to <hi>injoie</hi> and <hi>joie</hi> in our friends, that when they <hi>die,</hi> yet wee may <hi>live;</hi> that their <hi>death</hi> may nor bee our <hi>death;</hi> that wee may follow them <hi>to</hi> the Grave, and not <hi>into</hi> the Grave.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Wee must beware of excessive Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> And since man is a mortal thing, why should wee put such confidence in him? <hi>Put not your trust in Princes</hi> (saie's David) <hi>nor in the son of man, in whom there is no help.</hi> Why? <hi>His breath goeth out, hee returneth to his earth: in that verie daie his thoughts perish, Psalm</hi> 146.3, 4. Mortal hee is, and not to bee confided in. Had hee been still immortal, hee had not been to bee trusted in; much less now. Manie a man build's high hopes on such or such a friend: hee trust's one daie to bee, or to do thus and thus: but his friend die's, and down fall<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> his hopes to the verie ground. Thus <hi>Cesar Borgia,</hi> that wicked son of a more wicked father, Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth, grounded manie designs on his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54874:15"/> to that Pope. But the Pope suddenly die's, and dashe's all. And <hi>Borgia,</hi> when hee heard of his death, cried out, <hi>I never dreamed of such an accident: now all my purposes and projects are stifled, and com to nothing.</hi> Hee that know's man <hi>well,</hi> know's him <hi>too well</hi> to trust him <hi>too much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Use 2. <hi>Since man is mortal, and must see death, let him know himself, and bewail himself, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, Know himself. David</hi> praie's to God <hi>to put the Heathen in fear, that they may know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs to bee but men, Psalm</hi> 9.20. But men? Why, did they think themselvs to bee more then men? It seem's they did. <hi>Empedocles</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Deus immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis haberi dum cupit Empedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, &amp;c. <hi>Hor. Art. Poet.</hi>
               </note> would needs bee accounted a God; and so would <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, and manie others: and Heathens they must needs bee that would bee so. Such as know God, know themselvs to bee but men, and would bee taken for no more. But a spice of this Heathenism and Atheism there is in most. Manie a man with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> conceit's himself to bee som<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>great one, Acts</hi> 8.9. Popes there have been so blasphemous, so heathenish, as to admit, with <hi>Domitian,</hi> that style, <hi>Dominus Deus noster,</hi> our Lord God. <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth,<note n="*" place="margin">Orâclo votis mundi modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris habenas, Et meritò in terris crederis esse De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> excepted not against the grossest fals Position that ever was, when in that devillish Distich hee found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self exalted in the place of God. And <hi>Paul the Third,</hi> hee, that when hee was takeing his leav of this world, said, Hee should now verie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54874:15"/> shortly bee resolved of three things which all his time hee had much doubted of: <hi>viz. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the soul were immortal: whether there were an Hell: and whether there were a God: made</hi> no scruple of <hi>makeing</hi> himself one. How dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> was <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Apostle!</hi> who style's<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> himself <hi>the least of the Apostles,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.9. <hi>Less then the least of all Saints,</hi> Ephes. 3.8. But the <hi>greatest of sinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. Mortal hee knew himself, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest of mortals hee accounted himself: and it will bee no sin, if everie man shall so account himself. God is pleased so far to <hi>honor</hi> som men, as to put upon them his own <hi>name. I have said, Yee are Gods, Psalm</hi> 82.6. But hee would not have them forget that they are men. Therefore hee add's in the verie next vers: <hi>But yee shall die like men; and fall like one of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> Lest they should bee exalted through the abundance of honor, hee presently laie's their honor in the dust. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Gods,</hi> but <hi>not immortal ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Let man Bewail himself.</hi> How will a man bewail the loss of a fair and comfortable estate, when hee is sunk down into a low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition! <hi>Call mee not Naomi,</hi> said shee, after her return to Bethlehem; <hi>call mee Marah: for the Lord hath dealt verie bitterly with mee. I went out full, and the Lord hath brought mee home again emptie, &amp;c. Ruth.</hi> 1.21. Wee cannot say the <hi>Lord</hi> hath made us <hi>mortal,</hi> but <hi>our selvs:</hi> wee might have continued <hi>happie</hi> and <hi>immortal</hi> still,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54874:16"/> had it not been our own <hi>fault</hi> and <hi>follie.</hi> The death of a dear friend strike's verie deep into us; specially if it hath been occasioned through our carelesness and imprudence. The loss of our immortalitie how should it <hi>affect</hi> and <hi>afflict</hi> us! How should the remembrance of it bee grievous to us! as the remembrance of Zion was to the Jews in Babylon. <hi>To have been happie,</hi> and not to bee so now, is a <hi>great unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. To have been immortal,</hi> (as wee were after a sort) and not to bee so still, but obnoxious to death; yea, more deaths then one, surely should bee oftner thought of, and more mourned for by us all, then usually it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Let man so know himself to bee mortal, and so bewail his mortalitie, as to Humble himself.</hi> And whosoever doth the first and second, will bee sure to do the third. A proud heart never troubled it self with the knowledg of it self, and sorrow for its mortall state: A proud <hi>eie</hi> never <hi>wept</hi> for it: A proud person is a verie stranger at home. But whosoever is well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with himself, and wisely conside'rs the state of man, cannot but bee an humble man. Humble hee will bee</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Towards God,</hi> whom hee hath offended and dishonored by putting himself out of that most comfortable and happie condition of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie wherein God made him. A disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor it is to a father when his son suffer's him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to bee cheated and cast out of his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: and well may such a son bee ashamed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54874:16"/> to look his father in the face: and well may hee carrie himself with the lowest humilitie towards him all the daies of his life. The poor Prodigal com's to his father in a most pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, humble, submissive sort; acknowledging, that haveing so dealt with him, and so undon himself, hee was <hi>no more worthie to bee called his son.</hi> Thus it is with everie childe of God: hee is full of sorrow and shame; hee <hi>creep's</hi> to God, and <hi>walk's</hi> humblie with him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Towards man;</hi> Whom though hee may <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed</hi> in som inward or outward qualifications, yet hee <hi>despise's</hi> and <hi>disdain's</hi> him not; hee <hi>look's</hi> not upon him as <hi>God</hi> may upon <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>man</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>beast.</hi> For hee know's him to bee his <hi>equal,</hi> once no less <hi>immortal,</hi> now no more <hi>mortal</hi> then himself: and therefore carrie's himself in a loveing, lowlie, sweet, sociable manner to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him.</p>
            <p>Use 3. <hi>Since man is mortal and must see death, let him reflect with sorrow and detestation, upon that which hath put him into such a condition.</hi> God made him immortal; and if hee had been <hi>ruled</hi> by him, hee had still <hi>continued</hi> so, and never <hi>seen</hi> death. Sin <hi>onely</hi> made him mortal, and put him into a <hi>necessitie</hi> of dying.</p>
            <p>Sin therefore should bee</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, Sorrowed for.</hi> First, and chiefly indeed, for the dishonor that was thereby don to so good and gracious a Maker: whom rather then to offend by the least degree of disobedience, wee should chuse to undergo the severest and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54874:17"/> greatest punishment that ever was or can bee inflicted. Secondly, for the dishonor and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that was thereby brought upon our selvs. 1. <hi>Dishonor;</hi> in that wee are made <hi>like the beast that perisheth.</hi> Between the bodie of a beast, and the bodie of a man, in respect of <hi>corruptibilitie,</hi> there is now no <hi>difference</hi> at all: the one return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the dust, and so doth the other. Manie a man when his estate is broken, his heart is broken too. To bee a bankrupt; to have been in great <hi>height,</hi> and now to <hi>fall,</hi> and break; to have <hi>shined</hi> gloriously, and now to bee in <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;</hi> to have been placed in the <hi>Firmament,</hi> and now to bee a fleeting <hi>meteor,</hi> is a great <hi>dishonor,</hi> and well may bee a stinging <hi>sorrow.</hi> That wee have so dishonoured our selvs by sin, that, as God said by an <hi>Ironie</hi> or <hi>Sarcasmus,</hi> Gen. 3.22. <hi>Behold! the man is becom as one of us, to know good or evil.</hi> So the <hi>beasts</hi> may most truly say, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold!</hi> man is becom as one of us, to <hi>die</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to dust, even as wee: how should this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our hearts, and fill us with grief. 2. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> in that when wee have ended this mortal <hi>life,</hi> wee are liable to eternal <hi>death.</hi> For by the first disobedience, wee not onely lost eternal <hi>happiness,</hi> (it had been som kinde of happiness to have staied there) but exposed our selvs to eternal <hi>miserie.</hi> So that, as the <hi>beasts</hi> may say, <hi>Behold!</hi> man is <hi>becom</hi> as one of us, in respect of <hi>mortal</hi> life: so the <hi>Devils</hi> may say, <hi>Behold!</hi> man is <hi>becom</hi> as one of us, in respect of <hi>eternal</hi> death: which without the infinite <hi>mercie</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54874:17"/> God, and <hi>merits</hi> of Christ, it is not possible for us to escape. How heavie their should that sin lie upon our hearts, which exposeth us to so woful a condition! But as it should bee sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed for, so</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Detested and abhorred.</hi> How should our hearts hate and <hi>rise</hi> against that <hi>sin</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee <hi>fell!</hi> That by sin wee are becom <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> should put us into an <hi>immortal</hi> hatred of it. Wee should endevor the <hi>death</hi> of that which hath been the <hi>caus</hi> of our death. The <hi>first</hi> sin, (which was the mother of our miserie and mortalitie) wee can onely mourn and sorrow for. Original sin, wee must not onely <hi>mourn</hi> for, but <hi>mortifie.</hi> That <hi>bodie of death,</hi> (as the Apostle style's it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.) wee must everie daie, with all our might, <hi>wrastle</hi> with laboring to <hi>enervate</hi> and overthrow it. And thus if wee endeavor the <hi>death</hi> of Original sin, wee shall prevent the <hi>birth</hi> of Actual sin: as the stopping the <hi>fountain</hi> will bee the drying up the <hi>streams.</hi> And truly, this one thing well considered, That our mortalitie is the <hi>fruit</hi> of our sin, would bee sufficient to <hi>sharpen</hi> our hatred against, and <hi>work</hi> in us an <hi>abstinence</hi> from all sins vvhatsoever: and make us say, Shall I not bee avenged on the mother in the daughter, on the first sin in Original? Shall I <hi>dallie</hi> vvith, and <hi>indulge</hi> the <hi>daughter,</hi> vvhen the <hi>mother</hi> hath been my <hi>undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> Shall I not, ought I not, to abstain from all, even the <hi>smallest</hi> sins, since the <hi>first</hi> hath prooved <hi>so</hi> pernicious? As the <hi>first</hi> made mee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54874:18"/> mortal, so the <hi>smallest</hi> is mortal. Were I now in the state of innocencie and immortalitie, as <hi>Adam</hi> once was, anie of the sins that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly committed, and accounted little, (an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious lie, a pettie oath, a wanton glance, yea, a wanton thought, and the like) would throw mee out of that happie condition, as that first sin did him, and make mee as mortal, as obno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious to death, to eternal death, as now I am. For <hi>all</hi> are of the <hi>same</hi> nature: and therefore I must take heed of, and abstain from all.</p>
            <p>Use 4. <hi>Since man is mortal, and must see death, Let him moderate his affections and hang loos to the things of this life. Wilt thou</hi> (saie's <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 23.5.) <hi>set thine eies upon that which is not? i. e.</hi> not permanent, nor certain. <hi>For riches cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly make themselvs wings, they flie as an eagle towards heaven.</hi> It may as truly bee said, Wilt thou that art not, set thine eies on riches? for thou certainly art a mortal creature, and must one daie fall down into the earth. And when wee fall down thither, were <hi>carrie</hi> nothing with us, except a rag, and a flower, and a board, or, <hi>at best,</hi> a piece of lead. Gold, and silver, and houses, and lands, and the like, which wee are so <hi>wedded</hi> to, and dote on, while wee live, wee must of necessitie bee <hi>divorced</hi> from, when wee go down into the Grave. A worm, how much dirt soever hee hath contructed by creeping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ground, leav's it all behinde him when hee creep's into his hole. It is<note n="*" place="margin">Kno'ls Turk. hist. pag. <hi>73.</hi>
               </note> storied of <hi>Saladine,</hi> a Turkish Monarch, that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54874:18"/> a shirt to bee fastened to to a spear it manner of an Ensign; and then proclamation to bee made by one of his Priests in these words: <hi>Saladine, Conqueror of the East, of all his mightie riches, carrie's away no more then This.</hi> A good lesson for Christians to learn; among whom, too manie are too apt to <hi>forget</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs, in <hi>gapeing</hi> greedily after, and <hi>grasping</hi> abundance of earth as though they were not <hi>mortal,</hi> but were to <hi>live</hi> here for ever. And so they seem to sing a contrarie song to those Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, of whom the Apostle speak's 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33. <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow wee shall die.</hi> But these earth-worms, thus, Let us add hous to hous, and land to land, and fill bag after bag, for wee shall never die. Such as these, when they com <hi>to die,</hi> (for die they must) how will they sing <hi>Loth to depart!</hi> With what <hi>difficultie</hi> will they bee <hi>divided</hi> from their <hi>dear</hi> Mammon! <hi>Lord, now lettest thou thy servant depart in peace,</hi> Luke 2.29. And, <hi>I desire to bee dislolved, and to bee with Christ,</hi> Phil. 1.23. is for a <hi>Simeon,</hi> that had his <hi>arms</hi> full of Christ; and not for them that have their <hi>hearts</hi> full of earth: and for a <hi>Paul;</hi> who accounted no more of gold, and silver, and all the riches of the Indies, then of dross, and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> dung, or of <hi>dogs-meat,</hi> that hee might win Christ, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. And not for <hi>such</hi> as thought not less of anie thing then of Christ; nor more of anie thing, then of their Mammon. Wee should <hi>use this world</hi> (saie's the Apostle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31.) <hi>as not abuseing it.</hi> His
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54874:19"/> reason is, <hi>Becaus the fashion of this world passeth away.</hi> Another reason wee may give: <hi>viz.</hi> Becaus wee our selvs pass avvay. Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever vvee have may bee taken from us; speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in such times as ours have lately been, and begin again to bee. Hovv vvonderfully since the first dravving the Svvord hath the vvorld been altered vvith manie a man! His fair estate hath served out it time, and is<note n="*" place="margin">Permutat do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos, &amp; cedit in altera jura. <hi>Hor. Epist.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> gon to a nevv master. That <hi>which is thine is mine;</hi> saie's the son of violence to the true<note n="†" place="margin">Haec mea sunt, veteres migrate, &amp;c. <hi>Virg. Ecl.</hi> 9.</note> ovvner: and so change's estates vvith him; take's his riches, and leav's him his ovvn povertie. But if vvhat vvee have bee not taken from <hi>us,</hi> surely wee must bee taken from <hi>it.</hi> And therefore let us <hi>desire</hi> vvhat vvee have not, and <hi>use</hi> vvhat vvee have, as not <hi>abuseing</hi> it: yea, as not <hi>abuseing</hi> and <hi>abaseing</hi> our selvs. Wee abuse the things of this life, and abuse and abase our selvs vvhen vvee <hi>desire</hi> them, and <hi>delight</hi> in them immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, and <hi>make more</hi> of them and of our selvs then vvee ought; accounting them <hi>stable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities</hi> vvhich are most <hi>unstable,</hi> and our selvs immortal vvho are but mortal. Wee <hi>advance</hi> our selvs indeed by <hi>accounting</hi> our selvs more then vvee are: but vve <hi>abase</hi> our selvs in <hi>fixing</hi> our <hi>affections</hi> upon such <hi>inferior</hi> things; no less then a man of <hi>noble birth</hi> dishonoreth himself by marrying his <hi>kitchin-maid.</hi> Though our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are mortal, our mindes are not so: and should bee taken up vvith higher and more noble objects. As for these things here belovv,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54874:19"/> though wee may <hi>desire</hi> them, and <hi>labor</hi> after a <hi>good</hi> measure of them; First, for <hi>supplying</hi> our necessities, and <hi>preserving</hi> us from contempt and injurie: Secondly, for <hi>distributeing</hi> to the necessities of our poor brethren, and for other pious and charitable uses: Thirdly, for the <hi>comfort</hi> of our posteritie; hee beeing <hi>wors then an infidel</hi> (as the Apostle saie's) <hi>that provide's not for his familie,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.8. Yea, <hi>A good man</hi> (saie's <hi>Solomon) leaveth an inheritance to his children's children,</hi> Prov. 13.22. Yet when wee <hi>have</hi> them, wee must not set our <hi>hearts</hi> upon them, but <hi>look</hi> upon our selvs as <hi>mortal</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who must one daie bee <hi>divided</hi> from all our earthlie comforts; and whose wisdom therefore it will bee so to <hi>stand affected</hi> to them, that wee may <hi>part fairly,</hi> and willingly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie reluctancie and looking back.</p>
            <p>Use 5. <hi>Since man is mortal, and must see death, Let him prepare for parting with this life.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Life is a <hi>sweet,</hi> but not a <hi>stable</hi> blessing: Death soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or later seizeth on all. There is no immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, no priviledg to anie. How then concern's it all to <hi>fit</hi> themselvs for their <hi>final</hi> farewel!</p>
            <p>Consider to this purpose these three things.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>That wee can die but once.</hi> Could wee die a <hi>second</hi> time, wee need not bee so careful for the <hi>first:</hi> for the second might amend a mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariage in the first; as the second Edition of a Book doth manie times the faults of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: and as manie a man and woman useth a second yoke-fellow with much more respect
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54874:20"/> and tenderness then the former. And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, as manie a <hi>dying</hi> man saie's, if his life might bee <hi>continued,</hi> hee would <hi>live</hi> better then before hee did: so manie a <hi>dead</hi> man, would <hi>resolv,</hi> if his life might bee <hi>restored,</hi> to <hi>die</hi> better then before hee did. But though there bee a <hi>second death,</hi> there is no <hi>second dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a corporal death.</hi> Therefore, since wee can die but <hi>once,</hi> how should wee prepare our selvs to die <hi>well!</hi> What can bee <hi>don</hi> but <hi>once</hi> in all his life, and is of singular <hi>concernment</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence,</hi> a wise man will endevor to <hi>do</hi> to <hi>purpose.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That it is a most difficult</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>thing to die well.</hi> To die is <hi>ordinarie:</hi> everie man can, and must do that. To die <hi>couragiously,</hi> and with a <hi>contempt</hi> of death, is no <hi>miracle:</hi> manie even among the Heathens have don it. But to <hi>die so,</hi> as not to <hi>die again</hi> afterward: to die so, as to have<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 14.32.</note>
               <hi>hope,</hi> and an <hi>heart</hi> full of <hi>joie</hi> in death: <hi>Hoc opus, hic labor est:</hi> this is one of the <hi>greatest</hi> works in all the world. The greatest part of men will not bee perswaded so, till they com to trie it: and indeed manie will not then. The Devil that prevailed with them before to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect (if not to puff at) a godlie life, and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel tending thereunto, prevail's with them then also to make but a puff of their own lives: and to conceiv that their death is happie if it bee <hi>quiet,</hi> and <hi>free</hi> from the <hi>convulsion-fits</hi> of an <hi>awakened conscience.</hi> Yet som there are, that, when they <hi>com</hi> to die, <hi>confess</hi> their former mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54874:20"/> they now finde it a most <hi>difficult</hi> work, which before they accounted most <hi>easie:</hi> they now see that a man's whole <hi>life</hi> should bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a <hi>preparation</hi> for death; they now break out into sad complaints of their<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spence of precious time, of their following un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie courses and companie; of their neglect of God, and happiness: they now wish,<note n="†" place="margin">O mihi praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritos referat si Juppiter annos!</note> O that my life were to begin afresh! Or, O that God would trie mee one year, or one moneth lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger! And if a <hi>freedom</hi> from death were <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaseable,</hi> they would <hi>purchase</hi> it with a great <hi>summ</hi> of monie. A great Knight of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom drawing towards his dissolution, was heard to say, <hi>That he would willingly buy his deliverance from it at a thousand pounds an hour,</hi> Yea, doubtless there are among the godlie, that <hi>look</hi> not on the <hi>mightie, weightie</hi> work of dying as a pleasant thing: they <hi>think</hi> not of it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out som <hi>affrightment</hi> and <hi>retreat</hi> of spirit, Though <hi>Elijah</hi> request God <hi>to take away his life,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.4. And <hi>Simeon</hi> sing, <hi>Lord now lettest thou thy servant depart in peace, Luke</hi> 2.29. And <hi>Paul, desire to bee dissolved, Phil.</hi> 1.23. Yet <hi>David</hi> praie's to God, not to <hi>take him away in the mid'st of his daies, Psal.</hi> 102.24. And <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> beeing summoned to die, complain's that hee shall bee <hi>deprived of the residue of his daies, Isa.</hi> 38.10, 11. These men were holie men as well as the other; and knew that <hi>this</hi> life is nothing to the <hi>next,</hi> and that death is the <hi>waie</hi> to it. Moreover, as they <hi>doubted</hi> not of eternal
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54874:21"/> life, so they could not but <hi>desire</hi> to bee presently possessed of it. Yet the great work of dying they are loth to com yet unto. They beleev (belike) they are not yet fit enough for it: and therefore they desire a longer time for prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. A <hi>great</hi> and most <hi>difficult work</hi> it must <hi>needs</hi> bee, which <hi>requireth</hi> a through <hi>repentance,</hi> a lively <hi>faith,</hi> a firm <hi>hope,</hi> perfect <hi>charitie,</hi> utmost <hi>patience,</hi> humble <hi>submission,</hi> holie <hi>contentedness,</hi> fervent <hi>praier;</hi> and manie such as these.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That according to our care or careles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in prepareing for death, will bee our consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it, and condition after it.</hi> With what a <hi>sad</hi> heart may an ungodlie man, that never <hi>made</hi> anie <hi>preparation</hi> for his death, lie upon his death-bed! Hee cannot fetch anie <hi>comfort</hi> from his <hi>former</hi> life. Hee consider's his <hi>neglect,</hi> or miserable <hi>misperformance</hi> of duties, his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> of grace, his <hi>manifold</hi> sins against <hi>manifest</hi> conviction, which are now to his <hi>conscience,</hi> as so manie <hi>swords</hi> in his <hi>sides;</hi> and make him lie upon <hi>feathers</hi> as upon <hi>thorns.</hi> Hee saie's unto death as <hi>Ahab</hi> unto <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 King. 21.20. <hi>Hast thou found mee, O mine enemie?</hi> Heaven hee cannot <hi>hope</hi> for, and Hell hee cannot but <hi>fear:</hi> Hee could bee content to <hi>miss</hi> of Heaven, so that hee might escape Hell: Hee wishes that either <hi>himself</hi> or his <hi>sins</hi> had never had a <hi>beeing:</hi> and would bee willing to die a <hi>thousand</hi> deaths one after another, if thereby his sins might bee <hi>expiated,</hi> or himself <hi>annihilated.</hi> Hee considers God's <hi>mercie,</hi> but cannot <hi>comfort</hi> himself with it,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54874:21"/> haveing so much <hi>abused</hi> it: hee <hi>look's</hi> on his <hi>Justice,</hi> as <hi>looking strictly</hi> on him, and readie to <hi>commit</hi> him to that <hi>infernal prison,</hi> from which there is no <hi>redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But with what a <hi>glad</hi> heart, and <hi>cheerful</hi> countenance may a <hi>godlie</hi> man, that <hi>prepare's</hi> for death, <hi>entertain</hi> it when it <hi>com's!</hi> It com's to him without a <hi>sting, (the sting of death is sin,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.56.) and therefore hee can <hi>safely take</hi> it, and <hi>put</hi> it into his <hi>bosom;</hi> as a man may a <hi>snake,</hi> when the <hi>sting</hi> is <hi>pulled</hi> out of it. Death is <hi>restorative</hi> to such a man, as the sight of the <hi>brazen</hi> Serpent was to them that were bitten with the <hi>fierie</hi> Serpents, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.9. It <hi>strike's</hi> indeed, but no otherwise then the Angel did <hi>Peter,</hi> to bring him out of prison, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.7. So death com's to the godlie, to <hi>deliver</hi> their souls from the<note n="*" place="margin">E corporum vinculis, tanquam è carcere, evola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt. <hi>Cic. Som. Scip.</hi>
               </note> prison of their bodies, and to <hi>return</hi> them to God that gave them. A godlie man <hi>expect's</hi> and <hi>prepare's</hi> for this guest, and therefore <hi>bid's</hi> it <hi>welcom.</hi> When men com up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us <hi>unexpected,</hi> and finde us not in such a <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture</hi> and readiness as wee <hi>desire,</hi> wee are not verie well <hi>pleased:</hi> and though wee <hi>love</hi> them well, wee could <hi>wish</hi> they had not <hi>com</hi> so <hi>soon.</hi> But if our selvs, and all about us bee in <hi>right order,</hi> the <hi>sooner</hi> they com, the <hi>better</hi> pleased wee are. So, to an <hi>unprepared</hi> heart, death strike's cold: but to a <hi>prepared</hi> one, it is as <hi>sleep</hi> to a wearie laborer; or <hi>cold waters</hi> to a thirstie soul; or <hi>good news</hi> from a far countrie: as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> speak's, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.25.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:54874:22"/>
            <p>How shall wee perpare for Death?</p>
            <p>First, <hi>By true repentance.</hi> Sin is the <hi>meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> caus of both first and second death. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance prevent's the <hi>second,</hi> and make's us readie for the <hi>first.</hi> Let death com when it will, it com's not <hi>unseasonably</hi> to a repentant soul, that hath endevoured to wash it self white again in it own tears: this <hi>washing work</hi> wee must do everie daie. Everie daie <hi>original</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption <hi>spot's</hi> us: everie daie by repentance wee must get out <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our spots, and endevor to <hi>stop</hi> up that cursed <hi>fountain.</hi> Everie daie we <hi>fall</hi> into sin: everie daie wee must <hi>rise</hi> again by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>By taking heed of all such things as must bee repented of. Do</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Cujus poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendum fuerit, nè feceris. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misisse cave quod mox mutare la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores.</note>
               <hi>nothing</hi> which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards thou must <hi>griev</hi> for, and <hi>wish undon;</hi> is a good rule: If wee observ it well, it will <hi>preserv</hi> us in such a <hi>sweet</hi> frame of spirit, as will make our lives <hi>comfortable,</hi> and <hi>prepare</hi> us for <hi>parting</hi> with them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>By leaving nothing undon till death approacheth, which ought to bee don before.</hi> To this most difficult work of dying well, what things are requisite I told you before. Now <hi>all</hi> our time is <hi>little enough</hi> for the acquireing of them. And the <hi>greatest</hi> measure of them that wee can get, wee shall finde <hi>little</hi> enough vvhen wee com to make our <hi>last</hi> use of them. It is <hi>utmost</hi> follie to <hi>neglect</hi> Grace, till wee are <hi>ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> into the Grave, and the lamp of our life is going out. Yet thus it is with the greatest
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54874:22"/> number of men. When they perceiv death comming to them, <hi>then</hi> they will provide for it, <hi>then</hi> they will repent, and beleev, and call upon God, and make their peace with Heaven. Thus the Devil <hi>blinde's</hi> and <hi>besot's</hi> them: thus they listen to his lure, and rather suffer him to <hi>cozen</hi> them into a <hi>conceit</hi> of dying well, though they never <hi>cared</hi> for liveing well, then God to <hi>perswade</hi> them, That if they would <hi>die well,</hi> they must <hi>live so;</hi> that they must provide <hi>all</hi> their daies for their <hi>last</hi> daie; that Repentance, and Faith, and other Graces are of more<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> worth then to bee so easily obtained; that if wee would have God <hi>hear us</hi> calling upon him in <hi>sickness,</hi> wee must <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>obeie him</hi> calling upon us in <hi>health;</hi> that Heaven will not bee at peace with us till wee are readie for death; and that wee must not <hi>conceiv</hi> our selvs <hi>readie</hi> for death, if wee <hi>prepare</hi> not for it till wee are <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> to die.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>By doing nothing in which wee would bee unwilling that death should finde us.</hi> Wee would bee loth that death should finde us ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>idle,</hi> or <hi>ill-emploied:</hi> that it should finde us not onely in anie ungodlie, unjust, intemperate action, but with an oath, or a curs, or a <hi>scoff,</hi> or a lie, or an obscene, wanton, foolish, <hi>idle</hi> word in our mouthes: yea, with anie sinful <hi>thought</hi> in our hearts. Abstain wee then care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully from all these. For these vvill make death most unvvelcom to us; becaus they argue an utter unpreparedness for it: novv vvhere
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54874:23"/> an <hi>unpreparedness</hi> is, there death is never <hi>welcom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>By doing all that wee do in such a sort, as if death were to seiz upon us in the verie act.</hi> Let a man <hi>so</hi> read, and hear, and praie, and sing Psalms, and communicate, and confer, and do <hi>all</hi> other actions, as if they vvere to bee his <hi>last,</hi> and hee vvill do them <hi>so</hi> sincerely, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, self-denyingly, as is possible for him to do; and so vvill bee in a preparedness for death, vvhensoever it shall com.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>By the dailie meditation of death.</hi> Death is the first of those<note n="*" place="margin">Mors tua, mors Christi, fraus mundi, gloria coeli, Et dolor inferni, sunt meditanda tibi.</note> five things vvhich are commended to everie man's meditation. And vvhosoever shall think frequently vvith himself thus: <hi>Dust I am, and to dust I must return,</hi> Gen. 3.18. <hi>My earthlie hous of this tabernacle must bee dissolved,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1. <hi>Here I have no continuing citie,</hi> Hebr. 13.14. Neither noble parentage, nor large patrimonie, nor high ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, nor vast riches, nor excellent beautie, nor firm strength, nor rare endovvments, nor <hi>anie thing,</hi> can keep life and soul, or <hi>rather</hi> soul and bodie alvvaies together: implacable death, maugre all that the most learned Physicians can do to the contrarie, vvill at last <hi>plunder</hi> this <hi>earthlie</hi> hous, and make mee <hi>keep open hous</hi> for everie <hi>worm</hi> that com's. Sin hath put mee into a <hi>necessitie</hi> of departing hence: it is God's <hi>mercie</hi> that I have continued thus <hi>long</hi> undis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved; hovv soon his Justice may command my dissolution, hee onely knovv's: obnoxious
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54874:23"/> I am everie <hi>moment</hi> to the devourer of men: Death may <hi>sweep</hi> away this <hi>dust</hi> this verie <hi>daie,</hi> yea, this <hi>hour,</hi> yea this <hi>minute,</hi> while I am in the mention of it: <hi>Wheresoever</hi> I am, <hi>whatsoever</hi> I do, I may bee reached by the <hi>inevitable</hi> stroak of <hi>impartial</hi> death. Whosoever, I say, shall frequently think thus with himself, shall finde the fruit of it. <hi>Such</hi> a man, and <hi>onely such</hi> a man, is <hi>likely</hi> to bee <hi>ripe</hi> and <hi>readie</hi> for death, com when it will: like a <hi>good hous-keeper</hi> that keep's a constant table, and hath alwaies great store of good provision about his hous, fit to entertain anie guest that com's. <hi>Such</hi> a man is likelie to have his heart in order, and his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts even, and to look death in the face with joie, and to take well all that death doth, as knowing that (as one said,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epist. Ench. cap. <hi>79.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Anytus and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litus can kill mee, but cannot hurt mee,</hi> so) death can do him no <hi>harm;</hi> but <hi>open's</hi> a <hi>passage</hi> for him into <hi>Paradise;</hi> where hee shall bee <hi>troubled</hi> no more with <hi>Death,</hi> or <hi>Sin,</hi> or <hi>Satan;</hi> but <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> with <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Glorie,</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> to all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>By frequent discours of Death.</hi> And if it bee much in our <hi>Meditation,</hi> it cannot but bee somtimes in our <hi>Communication.</hi> For what the <hi>minde</hi> run's on, the <hi>mouth</hi> will talk of: as what a<note n="*" place="margin">Omnia quae sensu volvuntur vota diurno, Pectore sopito reddit amica qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. <hi>Claudian.</hi>
               </note> man do's or desire's in the daie, hee commonly dream's of in the night. Now among all things that men discours of, nothing <hi>should</hi> bee more <hi>seriously,</hi> nothing <hi>can</hi> bee more <hi>profitably</hi> discoursed of then <hi>Death,</hi> which will
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54874:24"/> put an <hi>end</hi> to all discours. To <hi>discours</hi> of <hi>death</hi> will <hi>dispose</hi> us for <hi>death,</hi> and <hi>make</hi> us more <hi>fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> with it, and less <hi>fearful</hi> of it. It argue's utter <hi>unfitness</hi> for death, when men are <hi>not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to <hi>speak</hi> of it, till they are not <hi>able</hi> to <hi>speak</hi> of it; and not <hi>willing</hi> to <hi>hear</hi> of it, till they <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hear</hi> of it. It is storied of <hi>Lewis</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh King of France of that name, That fearing that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Arist. Eth. ad Nic. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>King of Terrors,</hi> (as <hi>Bildad</hi> style's Death, <hi>Job</hi> 18.14.) hee strictly charged, that <hi>none</hi> should <hi>so much</hi> as <hi>name</hi> it within his <hi>Court.</hi> (So <hi>bitter is the remembrance of Death to a man that liveth at rest in his possessions, to a man that hath nothing to vex him, and that hath prosperitie in all things,</hi> as the Wise-man saie's, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 41.1.) How much short was this Christian of that Heathen, <hi>Philip,</hi> King of Macedonia! who commanded a trumpet to bee sounded everie morning at his chamber-window, and then these words to bee uttered with a loud voice,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>King Philip, remember that you are but a mortal man.</hi> How shall this Heathen rise up in <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> against manie millions of Christians and <hi>condemn</hi> them! who will <hi>distaste,</hi> and it may bee <hi>deride discours</hi> of <hi>Death.</hi> Talk of <hi>sitting</hi> for the Grave, and they will <hi>think</hi> you go about to <hi>burie</hi> them <hi>alive.</hi> With whom therefore when they com to die, it may bee as it was with <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the Emperor: Hee, drawing towards his dissolution, brake out into this bitter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint,<note n="*" place="margin">Animula vagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, blandula, hospes, comésque corporis, quae nunc abil is in loca, Pallidula, rigida, tristia, nec, ut soles, d<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis joeos, &amp;c. <hi>Dion. Cassino.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>O my soul what will becom of thee? whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will death send thee? into what a dreadful
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54874:24"/> place will the Devils drag thee? now thy jollitie must bee no more.</hi> Take wee heed of such <hi>jollitie</hi> and <hi>vanitie</hi> as will <hi>render</hi> the <hi>discours</hi> of death <hi>distasteful,</hi> and make us <hi>unfit</hi> for the sudden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of it. Rather let us bee willing in the <hi>mid'st</hi> of our <hi>Feasts</hi> and mirth at anie <hi>time,</hi> to <hi>entertain</hi> thoughts, and to <hi>exchange</hi> discours thereof: which will <hi>excellently season</hi> everie <hi>dish,</hi> and <hi>preserv</hi> us from that <hi>excess</hi> which wee are too <hi>apt</hi> to <hi>fall</hi> into. <hi>Herodotus</hi> reporteth, That<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Herod. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>78.</hi>
               </note> great men among the Egyptians, when they made a Feast, caussed a dead man made in wood, as lively as might bee, to bee brought in, and shewed to everie one of the guests, with these words: <hi>Look on this and drink; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light thy self so now, as knowing that thou shalt bee such an one when thou art dead.</hi> It were not amiss if the same practise were among great persons everie where. It might restrain them haply, not onely from <hi>too liberall</hi> an use of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but also from that <hi>loosness</hi> and <hi>lewdness</hi> of <hi>language,</hi> wherewith manie times they <hi>defile</hi> their own mouthes, and <hi>griev</hi> the hearts of such among them as <hi>fear</hi> God; who had rather <hi>fast,</hi> then bee so <hi>feasted.</hi> And <hi>well</hi> it were for <hi>prepareing</hi> men for <hi>Death,</hi> if not <hi>onely</hi> at all their <hi>meals,</hi> but at all their <hi>meetings;</hi> they were <hi>enjoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> to make a <hi>Grave,</hi> and <hi>serious</hi> mention of that, which will <hi>dissolv</hi> our <hi>meetings</hi> and our <hi>selvs</hi> too, wee cannot tell <hi>how soon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly, and lastly, <hi>By a right going to the hous of mourning.</hi> A <hi>right going</hi> I say: not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54874:25"/> such as <hi>commonly</hi> wee <hi>make. David</hi> saie's of his enemie thus, <hi>If hee com to see mee, hee speaketh vanitie: his heart gathereth iniquitie to it self, when hee goeth abroad, hee telleth it, Psalm</hi> 41.6. If it bee not <hi>altogether</hi> so <hi>ill</hi> with us, when wee go to <hi>visit</hi> the sick, or to <hi>burie</hi> the dead, yet it is ill <hi>enough.</hi> Wee look upon the sick person, wee see him laid along on his bed, unable to turn, or to feed himself; wee see death in his face, wee see his tears, wee hear his sighs, and groans, and lamentations. One would think that such an <hi>object</hi> should make us <hi>retire</hi> into our selvs, and <hi>work well</hi> upon us, but it <hi>seldom</hi> doth: wee <hi>return</hi> as <hi>mindeless,</hi> and <hi>unfit</hi> to die, as wee vvent. So vvee go to the <hi>Funeral:</hi> vvee see the <hi>Corps;</hi> vvee see it put into the <hi>Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin;</hi> vvee see <hi>mourning,</hi> but vvee do <hi>nothing,</hi> for the most part, <hi>aright.</hi> Wee eat and drink, and talk as <hi>pleasantly,</hi> as if vvee vvere at a <hi>Wedding,</hi> and not at a <hi>Funeral.</hi> So that as one said to a Philosopher, vvho, vvhen the ship vvas in verie great danger of beeing cast avvay by a grievous tempest, minded nothing, but imploied his tongue in asking manie trifleing questions:<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Agell.</note>
               <hi>Wee are in a most sad and sinking condition, and do'st thou trifle thus?</hi> So it may bee said to us, You are com to the hous of <hi>Mourning,</hi> and are you so <hi>merrie?</hi> You see a man dead <hi>before</hi> you, and do you think that you shall <hi>never</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv? Wee follovv the <hi>Corps</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> vvee see it <hi>committed</hi> to the <hi>Earth,</hi> wee hear the <hi>Funeral Sermon;</hi> Can vvee chuse novv but
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54874:25"/> bring death <hi>home</hi> with us in our <hi>hearts,</hi> and make <hi>preparation</hi> for it? But alas, how little do wee? Who almost think's with himself, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die tibi, cras mihi:</hi> thou art buried to daie, my turn may bee to morrow. Wee procrastinate, and <hi>put far away the evil daie, Amos</hi> 6.3. as though with the drunkards of Ephraïm, wee had <hi>made a covenant with death, and were at an agreement with Hell, Isa.</hi> 28.15. How few are there that can say with <hi>Francis Borgia,</hi> a Spanish Courtier? Hee,<note n="*" place="margin">Ribaden De vitâ Fr. Borgiae. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> haveing been at the Funeral of the Empress, and considering how little a Grave had devoured all earthlie Greatness, said when hee came home, <hi>Augustae mors mihi vitam attulit; The death of the Empress hath brought mee life;</hi> and forthwith became a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfuly<note n="*" place="margin">Totus mutatus est in melius. Ibid</note> reformed man. If wee go aright to the <hi>hous of Mourning,</hi> wee go more <hi>willingly</hi> to it then to the <hi>hous of Feasting:</hi> becaus as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> saie's, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.2. it is <hi>better</hi> to go to <hi>that</hi> then to <hi>this.</hi> And wee <hi>return</hi> more <hi>wise,</hi> more <hi>weaned</hi> from the <hi>world,</hi> more <hi>willing</hi> to <hi>die,</hi> more <hi>prepared</hi> to die, then when wee <hi>went.</hi> As one saie's to another in the Poët,<note n="*" place="margin">Nunquam ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedo, quin abs te abeam doctior, <hi>Ter.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>I never com to you but I return better instructed:</hi> so may wee say, if wee bee not <hi>wanting</hi> to our selvs, when wee visit the Sick, or perform the last office to the dead: <hi>Wee never do so, but wee return much better.</hi> Everie thing that wee either <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> or <hi>hear,</hi> is a <hi>real Sermon</hi> to us, and <hi>call's</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to make a good <hi>use</hi> of it. Everie <hi>Funeral-daie</hi> is an <hi>Humiliation-daie,</hi> which <hi>setteth</hi> the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54874:26"/> heart in a <hi>good</hi> frame, and so keepeth it <hi>a great</hi> while after. And therefore, such as <hi>truly desire</hi> to prepare for Death, will as <hi>willingly</hi> go to a dying man, and <hi>attend</hi> him when hee is dead, as those <hi>persons</hi> that <hi>desire</hi> to <hi>discharge conjugal</hi> duties, will <hi>desire</hi> to bee <hi>present</hi> at <hi>Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial</hi> contracts, where their <hi>duties</hi> are <hi>discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed</hi> of.</p>
            <p>Now as wee ought <hi>everie daie</hi> to prepare for death, that wee may say with the Apostle <hi>Paul, I die daily,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.31. (though<note n="*" place="margin">Mortis pericula adeo. <hi>Metonymia effecti Hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica.</hi> Sic 2 Cor. 11.23. in morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus saepe se fuisse scribit. <hi>Pisc. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </note> hee speak's it in another sens:) so ought wee more <hi>specially</hi> to do it, the <hi>nearer</hi> wee are to our <hi>Close.</hi> It is reported of the <hi>birds</hi> of <hi>Norwey,</hi> that they are of <hi>swifter</hi> flight then the birds of anie <hi>other</hi> countrie: not becaus nature hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed upon them more <hi>agilitie</hi> of wing; but by an <hi>instinct</hi> they know the <hi>daies</hi> there to bee exceeding <hi>short,</hi> and therefore they <hi>hasten</hi> the more unto their nests. A stone the <hi>nearer</hi> it fall's to the Center, the <hi>faster</hi> it mov's. The Sun, the nearer it is to it going down, the more glorious it look's. Thus it should bee with us: The <hi>shorter</hi> our time is, the more <hi>haste</hi> wee should make: the <hi>nearer</hi> wee are to our <hi>descent</hi> into the <hi>Grave,</hi> the more <hi>vigorous</hi> should bee our <hi>preparation</hi> for it. Thus if wee <hi>do,</hi> when wee are cast on our bed of <hi>sickness,</hi> and receiv a <hi>summons</hi> to <hi>appear</hi> in another world, wee shall bee <hi>fitted</hi> to part with this. A man that <hi>dieth daily,</hi> hath <hi>little</hi> to <hi>do</hi> when hee <hi>com's</hi> to <hi>die</hi> but to <hi>die:</hi> and hee may die not onely patiently,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54874:26"/> but delightfully;<note n="*" place="margin">Qui capit dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solvi &amp; esse cum Christo, non pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienter moritur, sed patienter vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, &amp; delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter moritur.</note> as <hi>Augustin</hi> saie's, <hi>Hee that desire's to bee dissolved, and to bee with Christ, doth not die patiently; but live's patiently, and die's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfully.</hi> Hee know's that as his <hi>earthlie</hi> friends will <hi>carefully commend</hi> his <hi>Bodie</hi> to the <hi>Earth:</hi> so his <hi>heavenly</hi> friends, the holie An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels will <hi>cheerfully conveigh</hi> his <hi>Soul</hi> into <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> This <hi>good</hi> office these holie Angels <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> to everie <hi>godlie</hi> Soul by the <hi>appointment</hi> of God. The Soul, <hi>doubtless,</hi> can finde the <hi>waie back again</hi> to Heaven of it <hi>self:</hi> beeing <hi>free</hi> from the <hi>Bodie</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> it <hi>asscend's</hi> to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as <hi>naturally</hi> as the <hi>Bodie descend's</hi> to the Earth; or as a wicked Soul, <hi>unpurged</hi> of it <hi>sin, fall's down</hi> to Hell. Notwithstanding it <hi>pleaseth God</hi> to send forth these ministring Spirits, and it <hi>pleaseth them</hi> exceedingly to com, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie <hi>their</hi> Souls who are to bee <hi>Heirs of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and to <hi>preserv</hi> them in <hi>safetie</hi> from the <hi>Prince of the power of the Air,</hi> and his <hi>hellish</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, who would gladly <hi>intercept</hi> the asscending <hi>Soul,</hi> and <hi>hale</hi> it into his own <hi>Quarters.</hi> This, <hi>I say,</hi> a man that <hi>die's daily,</hi> and so is <hi>prepared</hi> for <hi>Death,</hi> is <hi>certain</hi> of, and therefore <hi>die's delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</hi> Let it bee the care of us all so to prepare for Death, that wee may so die.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I Have now don with my Text. But should I do no more, I am sure you would say, that I did not enough. Wee use to say to them that comming from <hi>London</hi> bring no <hi>News</hi> with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54874:27"/> them, <hi>They deserv to bee sent back again.</hi> Should I com down from this place without speaking somwhat of this thrice-worthie Ladie, whose earthlie part wee are now to deliver to the hand of the Grave, as those blessed Spirits have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie conducted her Better part into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous presence of her God, you would all say, <hi>It were fit to force mee up again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know you all have a longing desire to hear som Commemoration of her manifold worth. My purpose is to save your <hi>longing,</hi> by giveing you a <hi>Taste</hi> of that whereof you desire so much. I shall present you with the vast <hi>Earth</hi> in a small <hi>Map;</hi> with <hi>Homer's Iliads</hi> in a <hi>nut-shel;</hi> with a <hi>Chapter</hi> in the <hi>Contents;</hi> or with a <hi>Book</hi> in the <hi>Index:</hi> leaving enlargment to your selvs, and knowing that by your meditation, the few <hi>Grains</hi> which I shall <hi>scatter</hi> may greatly <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie,</hi> and my <hi>little cloud,</hi> no bigger then a man's <hi>hand,</hi> may <hi>mask</hi> the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>whole</hi> Heaven.</p>
               <p>Should I now put you to the exercise of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hour's patience, I make no question but you would all say of my discours of Her, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie have said of her noble Husband's Epitaph: <hi>It is true, all that is said of him, everie word.</hi> Much more might have been said there of Him, but specially of Her. But such was her <hi>modestie,</hi> that although in that <hi>Magnificent Monument</hi> which shee erected for him, shee caussed her self to bee <hi>lai'd</hi> by him in <hi>full</hi> proportion; yet shee would not <hi>suffer</hi> her <hi>Epitaph</hi> to <hi>bear</hi> anie <hi>proportion</hi> with <hi>His.</hi> Shee conceived the <hi>most</hi> that could be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54874:27"/>
                  <hi>said</hi> of Him <hi>too little;</hi> and the <hi>least</hi> that could bee <hi>said</hi> of Her self <hi>too much. Unwilling</hi> shee was to have <hi>anie thing</hi> at all said of <hi>Her self.</hi> When that might not bee, shee would by no means al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of anie more then This, <hi>Her Observance of her dearest Husband while shee enjoied him; Her Remembrance of him by that Monument when shee had lo'st him.</hi> Onely <hi>one thing</hi> more was added, but much <hi>against</hi> her will: viz. <hi>That her other exquisite Virtues were forbidden by her excessive Modestie, to make their appearance in that Marble.</hi> I will now acquaint you, (and it is my great Grief, as it is all yours, and all the countrie's also, that I can so soon acquaint you,) what I mean't by those other Virtues: And I desire you to expect no more but what may bee a Supplement or Addition to her Epitaph.</p>
               <p>Her <hi>Birth</hi> was none of Hers: and therefore <hi>cannot bee</hi> either her <hi>Virtue</hi> or her <hi>Prais.</hi> High <hi>Descent,</hi> and mightie <hi>Names,</hi> far fetch't, are but<note n="*" place="margin">Ista vestra no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina nunquam sum admiratus: viros eos qui ea vobis reliquissent magnos arbitro <hi>Cic. Appio Pulcro. Epist.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 3.</note>
                  <hi>Names;</hi> and the <hi>names</hi> of <hi>others too. Scarcely</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Genus &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vos, &amp; quae non fecimus ipsi. Vix ea <hi>nostra</hi> voco. <hi>Ovid. Met. l.</hi> 13.</note>
                  <hi>can wee call</hi> ours <hi>what our selvs are not the</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors <hi>of. And, not manie Generations, and a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of mouldie Statues, but</hi> onely <hi>Virtue,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Tota licèt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres exornent undique cerae Atria, nobilitas sola est atque unico virtus. <hi>Juv. sat.</hi> 8.</note>
                  <hi>give's the Character of</hi> truly-<hi>Noble.</hi> Thus even <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> could say. How far then should <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> bee from committing Idolatrie with stocks, and worshipping Images! Asscribeing so much, I mean, to Families, and esteeming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs or others truly-Noble, if their progenitors have been so. Nobilitie is not <hi>hereditarie</hi> but <hi>inherent;</hi> not <hi>relative</hi> and <hi>transmitted,</hi> but <hi>moral</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:54874:28"/> and <hi>personal;</hi> or <hi>at least</hi> not so much. Apt wee are to <hi>give</hi> much <hi>Honor</hi> to the verie <hi>Shadow</hi> of Nobilitie. But when to the <hi>Shadow</hi> there is <hi>added</hi> the <hi>Substance,</hi> Nobilitie <hi>inherent</hi> to No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie <hi>hereditarie,</hi> there wee ow a <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>double Honor.</hi> And such a <hi>Debt</hi> wee <hi>owed</hi> to this <hi>Noble Ladie,</hi> so <hi>conspicuous</hi> in both.</p>
               <p>Her <hi>entrance</hi> was <hi>earlie</hi> into the <hi>Conjugal</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. (Such <hi>Fruit,</hi> so <hi>rare,</hi> so <hi>ripe,</hi> could not <hi>continue</hi> long <hi>ungathered.</hi>) Yet not <hi>sooner</hi> then shee was <hi>fit</hi> for it. Shee knew that <hi>her takeing</hi> of a <hi>Second-Self,</hi> was a <hi>Self-denying work:</hi> and therefore shee <hi>resigned</hi> both her <hi>reason</hi> and her <hi>will</hi> unto her <hi>Head.</hi> To whom shee was, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica</hi> the mother of St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> was to her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Patricius,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Reverenter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabilis, &amp; mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis. <hi>Aug. Confes. lib</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note>
                  <hi>Reverently amiable, and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> And from whom, for all the Virtues which an Husband can wish for in his Wife, shee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as <hi>much</hi> Honor, as anie daughter of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> can receiv from a son of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After they had <hi>drawn</hi> together in this <hi>yoke</hi> for the space of <hi>thirtie</hi> years, with as much <hi>mutual dearness</hi> and <hi>delight,</hi> as wee have heard of in <hi>anie;</hi> it pleased God to <hi>dissolv</hi> the <hi>knot,</hi> by takeing to himself, <hi>Praesidium, &amp; dulce decus, &amp; anima dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium;</hi> her support and honor, far <hi>dearer</hi> to her then her verie <hi>life.</hi> But then it pleased God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, to shew himself <hi>abundantly</hi> gratious to her. When hee had made her a <hi>Widow,</hi> hee made himself her <hi>Husband; supporting</hi> her, <hi>protecting</hi> her, <hi>comforting</hi> her, and <hi>enabling</hi> her to <hi>manage</hi> her <hi>great Estate,</hi> and to <hi>order</hi> her <hi>numerous</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54874:28"/> with such a <hi>measure</hi> of <hi>Prudence,</hi> as was <hi>admirable; specially</hi> if wee <hi>consider</hi> that her <hi>bodilie infirmities</hi> most <hi>commonly confined</hi> her to her <hi>chamber,</hi> and <hi>verie seldom permitted</hi> her to stir <hi>abroad.</hi> It is no <hi>wonder</hi> that the Senators and privie Counsellers of the Musulman-Monarch carrie themselvs with so much <hi>fidelitie</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actness</hi> towards him, though hee <hi>never com</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Hee hath his <hi>dangerous window</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vide Joannis à Chokier Thesaur. Polit. Aphorism. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi> p. <hi>148.</hi>
                  </note>, where hee can see and observ all their behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, though none of them can see him. <hi>Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> is it, that <hi>all</hi> in so <hi>great</hi> a Familie as <hi>this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die's,</hi> should bee so <hi>regular,</hi> so <hi>diligent</hi> in their places, so <hi>faithful</hi> to Her: who as shee <hi>never came</hi> among them, so had no <hi>window</hi> through which shee might <hi>over-look</hi> them. The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent adiministration of such a Familie, by such a secret Governess, hath often seemed to mee a<note n="*" place="margin">Sic parvis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere magna, &amp;c.</note> livelie representation of the admirable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the whole Creation by it invisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Governor. God's <hi>Wisdom</hi> is everie where <hi>visible,</hi> though <hi>himself</hi> bee not: So her <hi>influence extended</hi> to all her <hi>affairs,</hi> though <hi>her self</hi> were so <hi>retired.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>burthen</hi> of a <hi>weak</hi> Bodie shee <hi>continually carried</hi> about her. But shee <hi>bare</hi> it with <hi>singular</hi> patience; and <hi>improoved</hi> it to her <hi>spiritual</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. It is a <hi>blessed Weakness,</hi> which <hi>make's</hi> us <hi>make God</hi> our <hi>strength:</hi> a <hi>blessed Confinement,</hi> which <hi>set's</hi> the <hi>Soul</hi> at <hi>libertie,</hi> and set's it a <hi>long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> after more <hi>communion</hi> with <hi>God.</hi> Her great <hi>affliction</hi> it was, that shee could not <hi>visit</hi> the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54874:29"/>
                  <hi>Hous</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>attend</hi> upon the <hi>publick Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances:</hi> where hee hath <hi>promised</hi> his <hi>presence,</hi> and wee may <hi>exspect</hi> his <hi>blessing.</hi> What <hi>manie</hi> in these giddie daies <hi>depart</hi> from, shee most <hi>earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desired</hi> to <hi>repair</hi> to. But becaus shee could not <hi>go</hi> from her <hi>hous</hi> to the <hi>Church;</hi> shee made a <hi>Church</hi> of her <hi>hous:</hi> where for <hi>sundrie years,</hi> shee <hi>everie Lord's daie</hi> in the <hi>Evening</hi> (unless shee were hindered by <hi>extraordinarie</hi> weakness) heard the <hi>Preaching</hi> of the <hi>Word; strictly requireing</hi> the <hi>presence</hi> of all her <hi>Familie,</hi> and <hi>shewing her self</hi> an <hi>example</hi> of <hi>singular</hi> Reverence and Attention.</p>
               <p>It hath been <hi>observed,</hi> that shee never <hi>remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> out of <hi>one</hi> room into <hi>another,</hi> but shee <hi>used</hi> som short <hi>Ejaculations,</hi> with <hi>lifting</hi> up her <hi>eies</hi> and <hi>hands</hi> to <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her <hi>first</hi> imploiment <hi>everie daie,</hi> was her <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble address</hi> to <hi>Almightie God</hi> in <hi>secret.</hi> Her <hi>next,</hi> the <hi>reading</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and som other <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> books. A <hi>great Librarie</hi> shee had, wherein were <hi>most</hi> of our <hi>choicest</hi> English Authors. No <hi>sooner</hi> could shee <hi>hear</hi> of anie <hi>pious Book</hi> made <hi>publick,</hi> but shee <hi>endevored</hi> to <hi>make</hi> it <hi>hers,</hi> and <hi>her self</hi> the <hi>better</hi> for it. <hi>Much</hi> shee was in <hi>Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and able to give <hi>as good an account</hi> of what shee read; haveing an <hi>excellent understanding,</hi> as in <hi>secular,</hi> so in <hi>spiritual</hi> things. Findeing the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit</hi> of this <hi>cours</hi> to her self, shee <hi>commended</hi> it to her <hi>Children;</hi> whom shee <hi>caussed</hi> to read, in her <hi>hearing, everie daie,</hi> som <hi>portions</hi> of <hi>both</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staments. In the <hi>Afternoon</hi> shee spent <hi>som</hi> time as before in the <hi>Morning.</hi> About an <hi>hour</hi> before
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54874:29"/>
                  <hi>Supper,</hi> shee <hi>appointed som</hi> one of her Children to <hi>read</hi> som <hi>godlie Sermon</hi> in the <hi>presence</hi> of the <hi>rest,</hi> and of <hi>her self;</hi> frequently <hi>instilling</hi> into them <hi>sweet instructions,</hi> and <hi>exhorting</hi> them to a <hi>religious walking.</hi> A <hi>little before</hi> shee <hi>betook</hi> her self to her <hi>repose,</hi> shee <hi>commanded</hi> them all to <hi>com</hi> into her <hi>lodgings;</hi> where they <hi>sung a Psalm:</hi> (as the Servants also <hi>constantly did</hi> after Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they rose from the Table: men-servants in the Hall, and maid-servants in another place.) And <hi>whence,</hi> after manie pious <hi>exhortations,</hi> and her motherlie <hi>benediction,</hi> shee <hi>dismissed</hi> them: and then <hi>closed</hi> the daie as shee <hi>began</hi> it, with <hi>begging</hi> the <hi>blessing</hi> of <hi>God</hi> upon her self. And thus shee did <hi>constantly, everie</hi> daie.</p>
               <p>You cannot but observ, by what I have said, as a <hi>gratious</hi> and <hi>pretious</hi> spirit in her, so an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great care</hi> of leaving <hi>gratious impressions</hi> upon her <hi>Children.</hi> A verie <hi>fruitful Vine</hi> shee was, and <hi>manie</hi> were her <hi>Olive-plants</hi> about her <hi>Table. Som</hi> of them have <hi>seen death before</hi> her: <hi>Ten</hi> shee hath <hi>left behinde</hi> her; the <hi>same</hi> number in <hi>either</hi> Sex, and all here present. And <hi>all</hi> of them will with <hi>thankfulness</hi> to <hi>God acknowledg</hi> that they were as much <hi>blessed</hi> in their <hi>Mother,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> were in their <hi>Father,</hi> or as their <hi>Father</hi> was in his <hi>Wife.</hi> As they daily <hi>fell down</hi> and <hi>asked</hi> her <hi>Blessing:</hi> so <hi>they rose up</hi> (as the Children of the virtuous woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.28.) <hi>and called her Blessed.</hi> Next to her <hi>golden Chain,</hi> I mean that <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>Graces</hi> mentioned by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7. (wherewith shee was <hi>eminently beautified</hi>)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54874:30"/> and the <hi>ornament of a meek and a quiet spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4. shee <hi>accounted</hi> (with<note n="*" place="margin">Haec ornamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mea sunt. <hi>Val. Max. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emp.</hi> 1.</note>
                  <hi>Cornelia</hi> that noble Roman matron) her <hi>Children</hi> her <hi>chief Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Her <hi>earnest endevors</hi> were to <hi>adorn</hi> them with all <hi>virtuous</hi> habits, and to make them the <hi>true</hi> children of God. Shee <hi>knew,</hi> and would have them <hi>know too,</hi> that there must bee <hi>added</hi> to <hi>Great</hi> birth, the <hi>New</hi> birth: to great <hi>Kindred</hi> and <hi>Allies, relation</hi> to the <hi>Familie</hi> of <hi>Heaven:</hi> to a <hi>great Estate,</hi> the <hi>state</hi> of <hi>Grace:</hi> or els they would <hi>wish</hi> one daie that they had <hi>never been born.</hi> Shee <hi>failed</hi> not to <hi>tell</hi> them, that <hi>true Grace</hi> is <hi>true great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;</hi> and the <hi>more</hi> anie of them <hi>feared God,</hi> the the <hi>greater portion</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> they might <hi>expect</hi> from her.</p>
               <p>The <hi>last link</hi> in St. <hi>Peter's Chain</hi> is <hi>Charitie.</hi> And this shall bee the <hi>last Grace</hi> that I will <hi>speak</hi> of in this <hi>Elect Ladie.</hi> I doubt not to style her so, as St. <hi>John</hi> doth his, 2 <hi>John</hi> 1. Shee was <hi>much</hi> in those <hi>gratious practices</hi> whereby shee might <hi>make her Calling and Election sure: much</hi> in the <hi>duties</hi> of <hi>Pietie,</hi> as I told you before: <hi>much</hi> in the <hi>duties</hi> of <hi>Charitie,</hi> as I shall tell you now. But what need I tell you? You know more then I can speak. You know what<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 9.39.</note>
                  <hi>Coats</hi> and <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> this <hi>our Dorcas</hi> made while shee was with us. I can <hi>touch onely</hi> the <hi>Hem</hi> of her <hi>Garments;</hi> as the diseased people desired to do the hem of our Savior's, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.36. And O that by this <hi>Touch</hi> that I shall give, if there bee among you anie <hi>hard heart,</hi> it might now bee <hi>healed:</hi> if anie <hi>withered hand,</hi> it might bee <hi>stretched forth:</hi> if<note n="*" place="margin">1 John. 3.17.</note> anie
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54874:30"/> man that <hi>hath this world's good, and see'th his brother hath need, and shutteth up his bowels of compassion from him;</hi> hee might hence forward <hi>open</hi> his bowels to him: and so <hi>write</hi> after this <hi>excellent Copie</hi> which shee hath <hi>set.</hi> As our <hi>neighbor-Corporation,</hi> from whence our <hi>Countie deriveth</hi> it <hi>name,</hi> may for <hi>acts</hi> of <hi>Charitie</hi> at <hi>all</hi> times, but <hi>specially</hi> in <hi>these</hi> times of <hi>universal</hi> Dearth, bee a <hi>pattern</hi> to <hi>all</hi> Corporations: the <hi>Poor</hi> that are there (though verie <hi>manie</hi>) beeing verie <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably provided</hi> for by the <hi>singular</hi> care of the <hi>Chief</hi> Magistrate, whom God hath appointed for such a time as this: So may this <hi>most Worthie Person,</hi> whose Charitie I onely hint unto you, bee a <hi>pattern</hi> to all <hi>private persons.</hi> God had <hi>giv'n</hi> her the <hi>Blessing</hi> of a <hi>great Estate:</hi> and hee gave her a <hi>greater Blessing</hi> then <hi>that,</hi> an <hi>Heart</hi> to make a <hi>right use</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Everie daie,</hi> shee <hi>stretched out her hand to the Poor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 31.20.</note>
                  <hi>yea, shee reached forth her hands to the needie:</hi> relieving a <hi>great</hi> number at her gates; and giveing a <hi>charge</hi> to her <hi>Porter,</hi> that when there came anie verie <hi>aged,</hi> and others that <hi>complained</hi> of great <hi>losses</hi> in our late la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable times, if they <hi>seemed</hi> honest, hee should <hi>com</hi> and <hi>certifie</hi> her, that shee might <hi>enlarge</hi> her <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> towards them. Which if hee had <hi>neglected</hi> at anie time to do, and shee had known of it, it is <hi>likelie</hi> shee would have been as much <hi>displeased</hi> with him, as <hi>once</hi> shee was with <hi>another</hi> of her <hi>Servants,</hi> for <hi>neglecting</hi> a <hi>command</hi> which shee had <hi>giv'n</hi> him in <hi>reference</hi> to the <hi>Poor's refreshment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Everie Week,</hi> in these times of scarcitie, shee sent manie <hi>loavs</hi> of <hi>bread</hi> to <hi>manie</hi> neighbor-Towns; caussed her <hi>corn</hi> to bee sold in the <hi>markets</hi> by the <hi>smallest</hi> measures, that it might not <hi>exceed</hi> the Poor's
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54874:31"/>
                  <hi>abilitie;</hi> and <hi>allowed</hi> certain <hi>meals</hi> in her <hi>hous,</hi> to sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie <hi>poor</hi> neighbors, whose emptie bellies were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable in their pale faces. Who when they had <hi>hereby</hi> recovered their old <hi>complexion,</hi> and so <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> (as it were) a <hi>new life,</hi> shee <hi>rejoiceingly professed,</hi> that the <hi>sight</hi> of such an <hi>alteration</hi> in them did her as <hi>much good,</hi> as anie thing which shee <hi>ate</hi> her self.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Everie Year,</hi> at the return of our Savior's Nativitie, shee <hi>visited</hi> (as her Noble Knight had don <hi>before) all</hi> the Towns about her, with <hi>cart-loads</hi> of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Flesh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Continually,</hi> shee imploied <hi>manie poor old</hi> men and women in <hi>such works</hi> as were <hi>sutable</hi> to their <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>strength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Physician came to her hous, shee made <hi>inquirie</hi> whether <hi>anie</hi> were <hi>sick</hi> in the Town: that if anie <hi>were,</hi> they might <hi>partake</hi> of the same <hi>benefit</hi> with her self. But at all times, when anie wanted <hi>health,</hi> shee <hi>presently</hi> had <hi>intelligence</hi> of it, and most <hi>cheerfully communicated whatsoever</hi> shee <hi>conceived con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible</hi> to their <hi>recoverie:</hi> haveing not <hi>onely great</hi> store of <hi>Restoratives</hi> alwaies by her, but <hi>great skill</hi> in the <hi>application</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>To conclude. As our Savior Christ said unto the woman of Canaan, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.28. <hi>Great is thy faith:</hi> so wee may say of our <hi>Religious Ladie, Great was her Charitie.</hi> Shee knew right well, and effectually, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it seem's considered,</p>
               <p>That <hi>Faith</hi> is but a <hi>Fancie</hi> without the <hi>Labor</hi> of <hi>Love:</hi> for <hi>true</hi> Faith cannot bee <hi>idle,</hi> it is <hi>never out</hi> of <hi>work,</hi> 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.3. and it <hi>worketh by Love, Gal.</hi> 5.6.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Greater</hi> anie are, the <hi>Better</hi> they should bee: the <hi>more goods</hi> they have, the <hi>more good</hi> they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54874:31"/> should <hi>do:</hi> and, <hi>as they have opportunitie, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> do good to all,</hi> Gal. 6.10.</p>
               <p>That such as are <hi>Rich</hi> in this world, have a <hi>great charge.</hi> They are charged, not to <hi>bee high-minded, and close-handed,</hi> (which they are apt to bee) <hi>but to do Good, to bee Rich in good Works, readie to distribute, willing to communicate, so laying up in store for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs a good foundation against the time to com, that they may lay hold on eternal life,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.17, 18, 19.</p>
               <p>That <hi>the Wisdom that is from above, as it is pure and peaceable, gentle, and easie to bee intreated: so it is full of mercie and good fruits, without partialitie, and without hypocrisie,</hi> Gal. 3.17.</p>
               <p>That <hi>pure Religion, and undefiled before God and the Father, is this; To visit the fatherless and widows in their affliction, and to keep himself unspotted from the world,</hi> Jam. 1.27.</p>
               <p>Thus unspotted shee ever kept her self. As the Apostle saith, <hi>Who shall lay anie thing to the charge of God's Elect? It is God that justifieth. Rom.</hi> 8.33. So may I, Who can lay anie thing to the charge of this <hi>Elect Ladie?</hi> God had <hi>sanctified</hi> her: Not so, as to <hi>free</hi> her from the <hi>inherencie</hi> of <hi>sin,</hi> (for so hee sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth none in this life,) but so, as to free her from the <hi>Regencie</hi> of it, and from <hi>all</hi> such acts as would have prooved a <hi>spot</hi> and <hi>blemish</hi> to her: which <hi>all</hi> that <hi>knew</hi> her must <hi>need's</hi> acknowledg. And this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, That shee was like a <hi>choice Garden;</hi> not onely free from <hi>eminent weeds,</hi> but <hi>richly furnished</hi> with all manner of <hi>fragrant flowers</hi> and <hi>delicate fruits:</hi> or, like the <hi>glorious Sun,</hi> not onely <hi>free</hi> from <hi>Spots,</hi> but <hi>full</hi> of <hi>Light.</hi> All the <hi>Countrie</hi> knew her; as <hi>Boaz</hi> saith, all the<note n="*" place="margin">Ruth 3.11</note>
                  <hi>citie</hi> knew <hi>Ruth</hi> to bee a <hi>virtuous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:54874:32"/> And <hi>so virtuous,</hi> that I am <hi>confident</hi> this <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of <hi>ours,</hi> hath not <hi>anie</hi> virtuous woman (though it hath as <hi>manie</hi> as <hi>anie</hi> Countie in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> of no <hi>larger</hi> extent,) to whom that <hi>admirable commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in the <hi>last</hi> of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> is <hi>more agreeable</hi> then it <hi>was</hi> to <hi>Her.</hi> The Question is there, <hi>Who can finde a virtuous woman?</hi> As if shee were like the<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 7.14</note> waie which leadeth unto Life, and <hi>few they were that finde her.</hi> Were S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Lucie</hi> alive, hee would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer with as much joie, That <hi>hee once found her;</hi> as our whole Countrie speak's with sorrow, <hi>That it hath lost her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At her entrance into her last sickness (which was about a fortnight's length) shee <hi>conceived</hi> her <hi>Life</hi> to bee but of a verie <hi>short continuance;</hi> and therefore <hi>composed</hi> her self for her <hi>Dissolution.</hi> Yet her <hi>Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> shee <hi>dur'st not</hi> but make <hi>use</hi> of; whose <hi>singular</hi> abilitie and fidelitie shee had <hi>frequently</hi> experienced; haveing been <hi>raised</hi> up by them when shee was <hi>faln</hi> almost as <hi>low</hi> as the <hi>verie</hi> Grave: and who now say as <hi>Hector</hi> once,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Virg. Aen. 2</note>—Si Pergama dextrâ</l>
                     <l>Defendi possent, nostrâ hac defensa fuissent.</l>
                  </q> If shee had been Recoverable, wee had recovered her. But, as hee saie's,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Ovid. de Pont. lib. 1. El. 4.</note>Non est in Medico semper relevetur ut aeger;</l>
                     <l>Interdum doctâ plus valet arte malum.</l>
                  </q> The most learned Physicians cannot keep Life when God call's for it. No <hi>Antidote</hi> against <hi>Death:</hi> no <hi>Dosis</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> will <hi>free</hi> us from <hi>paying</hi> our <hi>last debt. Go</hi> wee must when our <hi>Life-lord bid's com.</hi> The <hi>last words</hi> of our <hi>Noble Ladie</hi> were, <hi>My God, I com flying unto thee.</hi> Presently after which shee took her <hi>flight.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:54874:32"/>
               <p>Now what shall I say <hi>more?</hi> Shall I tell you the <hi>greatness</hi> of our <hi>loss?</hi> I cannot. Shall I <hi>call</hi> for <hi>Mourning</hi> for it? I <hi>need</hi> not. I <hi>see</hi> mourning, I <hi>hear</hi> mourning; and more need there is of <hi>stopping</hi> then <hi>provokeing</hi> grief. What an <hi>innumerable</hi> companie of people, of <hi>all</hi> ranks is here, and <hi>all mourners!</hi> How do the <hi>Flowers</hi> of our Countie, (the <hi>Gentrie,</hi> to which shee was such an <hi>Honor;</hi> and the <hi>Clergie,</hi> to which shee <hi>expressed</hi> so much <hi>Love,) hang down</hi> their <hi>heads!</hi> Her <hi>Servants</hi> (to com nearer home) are <hi>free</hi> among the Mourners, as <hi>Heman</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Psal 88.5.</note> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that hee was among the Dead; <hi>despairing</hi> while they <hi>live,</hi> of <hi>regaining</hi> their <hi>lost</hi> happiness. But her Children <hi>lament, and weep, and mourn</hi> for their dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Mother; as that <hi>Mother</hi> did once<note n="†" place="margin">Mat. 2.18.</note> for her <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and will not bee comforted, becaus shee is not. But when <hi>David's</hi> Father and Mother <hi>forsook</hi> him (as now yours have don you,) <hi>Who took him up?</hi> Will not <hi>David's</hi> God bee your God? Doubtless hee will, if you will have him so. <hi>Turn</hi> (I beseech you) <hi>Lamentation into Imitation.</hi> Make your <hi>Parents</hi> your <hi>Patterns.</hi> Let none of their <hi>Virtues fall</hi> to the ground; but all be <hi>kept up,</hi> and <hi>live</hi> in you. They have <hi>set</hi> you excellent <hi>Copies; write</hi> you <hi>after</hi> them: <hi>Sons,</hi> after your <hi>Father; Daughters,</hi> after your <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> and endevor to <hi>honor</hi> your <hi>Selvs</hi> and your <hi>Sexes,</hi> as <hi>much</hi> as They have <hi>don.</hi> Our most <hi>Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarie Ladie</hi> I commend also to the <hi>imitation</hi> of all you, who desire to bee <hi>commended</hi> as accomplished either <hi>Wives,</hi> or <hi>Mothers,</hi> or <hi>Mistresses,</hi> or <hi>Christians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have now don, but that mee thinks I hear the cries of a <hi>mightie</hi> multitude of <hi>Poor</hi> people: who seem to bee so affected with the Death of their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactress,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54874:33"/> as <hi>Thomas</hi> was with the death of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> when hee said to the other Disciples, <hi>Let us also go that wee may die with him, John</hi> 11.16. And <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure</hi> for so <hi>good</hi> a woman, so <hi>full</hi> of good works and alms-deeds, som of them would <hi>even</hi> have <hi>dared</hi> to die. While shee lived, shee <hi>frequently filled</hi> their mouthes, and refreshed their bowels. And their <hi>mouths</hi> are <hi>full</hi> still: but it is of her <hi>Praises,</hi> and their own <hi>Forlornness.</hi> But their bowels who will refresh? <hi>They lament, and weep, and mourn, and will not bee comforted;</hi> unless it bee in the hopes of <hi>his</hi> speedie settling here, to <hi>whom</hi> now descend's so great an Estate, with the Examples of so much Nobleness. It is pitie, but that <hi>Charlcot</hi> should bee <hi>Charlcot</hi> still; pitie! but that when <hi>one</hi> generation thus passeth, <hi>another</hi> should com; and <hi>fill</hi> that <hi>Orb,</hi> which for so <hi>manie</hi> generations hath <hi>held forth</hi> to this Countie so great a <hi>Light.</hi> If this may bee, (and wee all desire and hope it speedily may) the <hi>less</hi> will bee our <hi>Lamentation</hi> for the <hi>loss</hi> of this most <hi>Excellent Ladie;</hi> whose <hi>Virtues</hi> did so <hi>shine</hi> among us, and whose <hi>Name</hi> shall bee alwaies <hi>to us</hi> as a <hi>most sweet Perfume.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="eulogies">
            <pb facs="tcp:54874:33"/>
            <p>THE MONUMENT<lb/>
               <hi>Of the Right Worshipful</hi>
               <lb/> Sir THOMAS LUCIE,<lb/> AND THE<lb/> Virtuous Ladie ALICE<lb/> HIS WIFE</p>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:54874:34"/>
               <head>Thomas Lucie <hi>MILES.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>GRI Varvicensis Decus &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciae. Antiquissimâ oriun<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>us Familiâ, Virtute nihil duxit Antiquius. Quâ Majoribus suis <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiam perillustribus emicuit (si fas dicere) major &amp; illustrior. Quantus extiterit in Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Patriae Amor, quanta Illius in Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Pietas, publica Regni Comitia (quibus saepenumero popularis Illum ardor inseruit abunde perhibent. Rei Familiari splendidis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sim<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ne<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> aut meliùs prospexit, aut minùs serviit; promentibus indies Liberalitate &amp; Magnificentiâ quae, Frugalitas condiderat. Patrem-familia<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> praesti<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it q<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>les perpauci. Famulorum si quem morbus corripuerat, &amp; Ipse statim malè habuit, adhibuit Medicu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, Suis sumptibus restituit. Qui Pater in Hero erga Servos <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cil èjudices quid fuerit in Patre erga suavissimam Pro<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em, in Marito erga di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectissimam Uxorem. Mensae (quae nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam non opipara) Bonus quisque gratissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
<pb facs="tcp:54874:35"/> accubuit, praefertim si Theologiam sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puit, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Musas imbibit: Quarum Ipse sitien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior dubium an scientior fuerit. Museum certè Animatum audiit. Neque minùs beni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gna Pauperculis Janua. Cui, famem omni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus eximenti, qui valedixit etiam benedixit. Multas operas, praecipuè nè nihil agentes malèagerent, quotidie exercuit. Multis Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidulis etiam Plaustra Cibariorum quotannis transmisit. Bellatorem Equum, qui apud Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum plurimus, &amp; nusquam loci pluris, nus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam generosior, animi gratiâ, saepiuscule pressit. Cui nisi callidiùs fuisset quàm Sibi moderatus (nam Equo intentior laesit Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stina) nondum Ille, quo fuimus felices, &amp; quo non alter fuit in Terris felicior, fuisset in Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis felicissimus. Nobis autem occidit, sibíque exortus est, <hi>Decembris VIII. Anno Domini M.DC.XXXX.</hi> Aetatis suae, <hi>LVI.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:54874:36"/>
               <head>Et Domina <hi>Alicia,</hi> Ʋxor Ipsius.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ilia &amp; Haeres <hi>Thomae Spencer,</hi> de Claverdon, Armigeri. Cujus exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias Virtutes prohibet hoc Marmore (quod nec illas capit) nimia super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitis Modestia. Hoc so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum patitur: Fuisse Conjugis, dum in vivis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, observantissimam; posuisse Mortuo hoc qualecunque Monumentum; factámque prae Amore atque Moerore (utì cernis) Marmoream.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:54874:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  </hi> Thomas Lucie KNIGHT;</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne of this Countie's greatest Glories. An Extract of a most Antient Familie. But a dis-esteemer of Birth, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of Worth. Wherein hee out-shone the brightest of his noble Ancestors. A singular and much honored Patriot. Witness the supreme Court of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: Whither hee was frequently sent by the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous and fervent suffrages of his endeared Countrie. His great Estate none could either bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter manage, or bee less servant to. What Fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie laid up, Liberalitie and Magnificence laid out. A loyal Consort, a numerous Off-spring, and great abundance of Attendents were never bles't with a better Governor. His servant's Sickness was his Sympathie, and their Recoverie his Cost. Beeing thus a Father in a Master toward his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, what must hee bee in a Father toward his most lovelie Children, and in an Husband to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his most beloved Ladie? To his Table
<pb facs="tcp:54874:35"/> (which was alwaies choisly sumptuous) all Good men were ever most welcom; especially if Profes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sors of either Sacred or Secular Learning. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, though hee were so rare a proficient, that hee was accounted a Living Librarie; yet was hee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessantly acted with an impetuous desire after a greater hight. His Gate was not less propitious to the Poor: whose Valediction to it was a Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; their Farewel an heartie Praier for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster's welfare. Manie poor Laborers hee daily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied, chiefly, That they might not by doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, learn to do wors. Manie Neighbor-Towns hee yearly refreshed, sending unto them plentiful Provision. The Great Hors was his great delight. Manie hee had, as generous and elegant as anie were; which hee frequently backed with as much skill as anie could. Had hee not better known to moderate his Hors then Himself, (for from his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light arose his Diseas) Hee, in whom his Familie, Friends, Countie, Countrie, were so happie, and then whom none was more happie on Earth, had not yet been most happie in Heaven. Our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness set, and his arose, <hi>Decemb. VIII. M. DC. XL.</hi> In the <hi>LVI</hi> yeer of his Age.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:54874:36"/>
               <head>And LADIE <hi>Alice,</hi> his Wife.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Aughter and Heir to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Spencer</hi> of Claver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Esquire. Whose ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite Virtues are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by her excessive Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie to appear in this Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Nor can they bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in it. Shee permitteth no more then this; That shee was most observant of her dearest Husband while hee lived; hath erected this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument for him beeing dead; And, through Love and Lamentation, is her self (as you see) becom Marble.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>